<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The churches lamentation for the losse of the godly deliuered in a sermon, at the funerals of that truly noble, and most hopefull young gentleman, Iohn Lord Harington, Baron of Exton, Knight of the noble order of the Bath, and his Maiesties lieutenaunt of the county of Rutland, at Exton in Rutland, the last day of March 1614. Together with a patterne of piety, and the power of godlinesse expressed in his life and death, who yeelded to nature the 27. of February, 1613. when he wanted two moneths of 22 yeeres of his age. By Richard Stock, pastor of Alhallowes-Breadstreet in London.</title>
            <author>Stock, Richard, 1569?-1626.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1614</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 147 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 73 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A12980</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23273</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S117806</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853016</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853016</idno>
            <idno type="VID">18375</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A12980)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 18375)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1258:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The churches lamentation for the losse of the godly deliuered in a sermon, at the funerals of that truly noble, and most hopefull young gentleman, Iohn Lord Harington, Baron of Exton, Knight of the noble order of the Bath, and his Maiesties lieutenaunt of the county of Rutland, at Exton in Rutland, the last day of March 1614. Together with a patterne of piety, and the power of godlinesse expressed in his life and death, who yeelded to nature the 27. of February, 1613. when he wanted two moneths of 22 yeeres of his age. By Richard Stock, pastor of Alhallowes-Breadstreet in London.</title>
                  <author>Stock, Richard, 1569?-1626.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[32], 105, [7] p. : ill., port. (woodcuts)  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Beale,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1614.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The first leaf bears a woodcut.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A sermon at the funerall of the L. Harington.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
                  <note>Some print faded and show-through; some pages stained.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Harington of Exton, John Harington, --  Baron, 1592-1614.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:18375:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18375:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18375:2"/>
            <p>THE CHVRCHES LAMENTATION FOR <hi>the loſſe of the GODLY:</hi> Deliuered in a Sermon, at the fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals <hi>of that truly noble, and moſt hopefull young</hi> Gentleman, IOHN Lord HARINGTON, Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron of <hi>Exton,</hi> Knight of the noble order of the <hi>Bath and his Maieſties Lieutenaunt of the</hi> County of <hi>Rutland,</hi> at <hi>Exton</hi> in <hi>Rutland, the laſt day of March</hi> 1614. Together with a patterne of Piety, and <hi>the power of godlineſſe expreſſed in his life and</hi> death, who yeelded to Nature the 27. of <hi>February,</hi> 1613. <hi>when he wanted</hi> two moneths of 22. yeeres <hi>of his age.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> RICHARD STOCK, <hi>Paſtor of Alhallowes</hi>-Breadſtreet in <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by IOHN BEALE. 1614.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:18375:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18375:3"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
                  <head>NODO FIRMO</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Virtutem antiquam haec ſpirant inſignia multam:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Et</hi> Nodo Firmo <hi>gloria firma manet.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sanguinis en quanto fueras dignatus honore?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Maior Auis meritis gloria facta tuis.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This ample Coate ſpeaks auntient vertues praiſe,</l>
               <l>Vnited with th'indoſſoluble knot;</l>
               <l>His greater merits nobler trophe's raiſe,</l>
               <l>To houſe and name, which neuer be forgot.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:18375:4"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
                  <head>SINGVLVM MILLITARE HONORIS </head>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ecce detus dant prima decennia principe dignum:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n coelis illum proxima pene locant.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This honour was he grac't with at tenne yeares;</l>
               <l>Before twelue more he climbes beyond the Spheares.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>I. P.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:18375:4"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>portrait of John Harington</figDesc>
                  <head>DOMINVS IOHANNES HARINGTONVS BARO DE EXTON &amp;c.</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <div type="poem">
               <lg>
                  <l>Aſpicis Herois vultum, graphicamque figuram:</l>
                  <l>Ingenium, Mores, pingere nemo poteſt.</l>
                  <l>Effigiem verae virtutis, Nobilitatis,</l>
                  <l>Candoris niuei, Relligionis habes.</l>
               </lg>
               <closer>
                  <signed>F. H. D. M.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <lg>
                  <l>In this dead picture, onely doth appeare</l>
                  <l>A Lord, and Lords ſole heire, to Country deare;</l>
                  <l>If his ſoules portrait 'twere, it would thee tell,</l>
                  <l>That here great Arts, vertues and grace did dwell</l>
               </lg>
               <closer>
                  <signed>I. P. Cant. Col. Syd. Suſs.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:18375:5"/>
            <p>In the Epiſtle Dedicatory, in the margent at the letter <hi>r</hi> read <hi>exonerans.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:18375:5"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE THE vertuous and worthy Ladies, <hi>the Lady</hi> LVCIE, <hi>Counteſſe of</hi> Bedford, vvith her Right Honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Mother, the Lady</hi> ANNE HA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RINGTON. Baroneſſe, together with <hi>her Honourable Siſter the Lady</hi> FRANCIS CHICHISTER: All increaſe of true <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and pietie.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He holy ſpirit of God by his Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man <hi>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Paul,</hi> tels vs, and teaches vs, that<note n="a" place="margin">1. Tim. 4 8</note> 
               <hi>Godlineſſe hath the promiſes both of this life preſent, and of that which is to come.</hi> Among which, this is none of the leaſt,<note n="b" place="margin">Pſal<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 112.6</note> 
               <hi>The righteous ſhalbe had
<pb facs="tcp:18375:6"/> in euerlaſting remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance.</hi> Namely, ſuch a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance as the wiſe man ſpeaketh of;<note n="c" place="margin">Prou. 10.7</note> 
               <hi>The memoriall of the iuſt ſhall be bleſſed.</hi> Such a bleſſing it is, as is<note n="d" place="margin">Pro. 22.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue great riches, aboue ſiluer and gold.</hi> For no man of any ingenious diſpoſition, but if hee had theſe two pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded to him, riches with ſhame, and pouerty and penu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry with true honour and good reputation, and free choiſe giuen him; but he would freely chuſe the latter before the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer: yea ſuch a bleſſing it is, that men who were able to iudge, thought it not inferior but aboue their naturall life. As that learned Rabbi, broght
<pb facs="tcp:18375:6"/> vp at the feete of <hi>Gamaliel,</hi> ſpeaking of his good reputation ſaith;<note n="e" place="margin">1. Cor. 9.15</note> 
               <hi>It were better for me to die, then that any man ſhould make my reioycing vaine</hi> And <hi>Tertullian</hi> by a ſpeech of his to the perſecuting tyrants ſheweth, that thus they eſteemed it, and profeſſed no leſſe to the world.<note n="f" place="margin">Ad Lenorem proxime damnan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do Chriſtianum, quam ad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eonem, confeſsieſtis labem pudi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>itae apud nos omni atrociorem poena, &amp; omni morte reputari. Tertull Apoll.</note> 
               <hi>VVhile you condemne,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>a Chriſtian matron to a baud, rather then to a Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, you openly confeſſe for vs, that we abhor the blot of Chaſtitie and honeſtie, more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all other puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts; yea then death.</hi> And this is that which the light of Reaſon teacheth men; that for a man to die honourably, is
<pb facs="tcp:18375:7"/> no death; for a man to liue diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honourably, is worſe then death. And as it is a curſe for a man, to ſuruiue his good name, ſo is it a bleſſing his good name ſhould ſuruiue him. So that, he which helps to keep the righteous in a bleſſed me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moriall or remembrance, hee doth but bring the promiſed bleſſing of God vpon the head of the righteous, help<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng to honour thoſe whom God would haue honoured, and who haue honoured God; yea, as I may ſo ſpeake, he helps to pay Gods debt to the righteous; hee ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing made himſelfe a<note n="g" place="margin">Debitorem ſe fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit promittendo. Auguſt.</note> 
               <hi>debter to them by promiſe.</hi> A thing that all ought to doe, and not vnbefitting any, no not
<pb facs="tcp:18375:7"/> the Miniſters of the Goſpell; when as our Sauiour Chriſt ſaith, concerning <hi>Mary;</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Mark 14.9</note> 
               <hi>Whereſoeuer this Goſpel ſhall be preached through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the whole world, this alſo that ſhee hath done, ſhall be ſpoken of in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of her.</hi> And by whom more then by the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the Goſpell? who if they muſt honour her, by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting what ſhe had done, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but one act of pietie per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed to Chriſt, how much more may they do it for thoſe, who haue performed many and manifold workes of pietie and charitie to Chriſt and his members? Vpon which ground, I tooke my ſelfe warranted to
<pb facs="tcp:18375:8"/> expreſſe the loue and honour I bore towards your deceaſed honourable ſonne and brother, in ſpeaking thoſe things I did at his funerals concerning his truely religious life and right bleſſed death, wherein I labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to make euident to others for imitation, that grace which God had made ſo emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent in him. The whole Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditorie were much affected with it, and many both godly and learned, both Miniſters and others deſired much to haue it publiſhed to the world, whereof diuers the ſame day ſet vpon, and ſince by letters haue importuned mee much, beſides others in the name of many (who haue but heard a
<pb facs="tcp:18375:8"/> flying report of the excellent graces and moſt worthy parts that was in him, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered by me) haue ſtill preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed me to imprint it, to make that common to others, which was ſo louely in the eares of thoſe that heard it. After all this I began to thinke, that this proceeded from the Lord, and to ſay with my ſelfe, as the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> to others,<note n="i" place="margin">Act. 11.17</note> 
               <hi>VVho was I, that I could let God.</hi> So, who am I, that I ſhould let God, thinking alſo with my ſelfe, that that which was ſo deſired of many, might be by the grace of God profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to many mo; knowing that God hath not onely, appointed his word to beget faith, and
<pb facs="tcp:18375:9"/> teach godlines, but by the ſame word, hath ſanctified the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of godly men, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke to godlines: as is manifeſt in holy writ; yea examples are of that force, that men are of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten won by them to the liking of the word, who before had either a hatred or diſtaſte of it; and after, by the word are wonne vnto God. Many men muſt ſee the Goſpell in the liues of the profeſſors of the Goſpell, before they will beleeue it in the mouthes of the Preachers of it. And as <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſaith of the Gentiles:<note n="k" place="margin">His quae dicun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur a no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> non in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenduni Gentiles, ſed his quae gerun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur a nobis Ho. <hi>70.</hi> ad Pop. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t.</note> 
               <hi>They doe not regard what things are vttered by vs, but what are acted of vs.</hi> So may I ſay of many who liue amongſt vs,
<pb facs="tcp:18375:9"/> and beare the name of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, they little regard either what we preach, or profeſſe, but what wee practiſe.<note n="l" place="margin">2. Pet. 3.1.</note> And if the huſbands may be wonne with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the word by the ſubmiſſe and meek conuerſation of their wiues; the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may others with the word by the holy conuerſation of thoſe who profeſſe the word, be wonne vnto godlines. And as by others, ſo I am perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the life and conuerſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this holy young Saint (ſo was he in earth, ſo is he in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen) of whom I will not heere ſpeake much, leſt any ſhould taxe mee with flattery. Yet this I will ſay (glorifying God that I can truely ſay it of him, not to honour him ſo much by
<pb facs="tcp:18375:10"/> it, as the Goſpell of Ieſus Chriſt:) that I challenge the whole armie of the vncircum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed Philiſtimes of Rome, to bring me forth the greateſt Goliath, I ſay not of the like age, honour and rancke, but almoſt of what age or degree ſoeuer, that euer ſhewed ſo much power of popery or the forme of ſeeming ſanctitie, as this young man <hi>Dauid</hi> did, the power of true pietie and godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. Let them then ceaſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying the hoſt of Jſraell, when they came hardly paralell our younglings with men of the beſt grouth they haue or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly haue had. But if I ſhold follow this matter I ſhold hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly keepe meaſure, and therfore I
<pb facs="tcp:18375:10"/> will content my ſelfe with this.</p>
            <p>Why I haue dedicated this to your name ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be ſtrange to any which know the great &amp; nie intreſt you had in the ſubiect, and ſo moſt right to the Sermon. To ſay nothing of my owne bond who haue recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued ſuch loue from him, for which I muſt and will honour all his; yea who haue ſo deepely taſted of the bountie of you his honourable mother. Accept it I pray you as a ſmale teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of my thankefull minde, &amp; as a true teſtimonie of that loue and reuerence that I haue borne to that grace of God which was manifeſt in him. The Lord hath greatly honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red you with the worty being
<pb facs="tcp:18375:11"/> and the bleſſed memory of ſuch a gratious Sonne, ſuch a godly brother, yea ſo honoured you as in all reſpects he hath hardly honoured any Mother, any Siſters; hauing giuen you, his honourable Mother, the fruit of all your great care, labour, and coſt you ſo naturally and religiouſly tooke, in tilling his young heart, wherein you not onely laboured by your ſelfe in his infancie, as another mother of<note n="m" place="margin">Prou 31.</note> the <hi>worthy Lemuel to inſtruct him,</hi> teaching your <hi>Timothie</hi> like another <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice</hi> (renowned in holy writ)<note n="n" place="margin">2. Tim. 1.5. &amp; 3.15</note> 
               <hi>The holy Scriptures of a childe,</hi> and ſeeking to plant in him <hi>the vnfained faith which dwelleth in you his
<pb facs="tcp:18375:11"/> mother.</hi> But alſo prouiding for him a worthy Tutor, a man of no leſſe piety then lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning (Oh that all of your ranke would doe the like, then might we hope for more religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and pietie among our Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie) who might perfect that your ſex had begun, but could not thorowly performe; and after moſt plentifully rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded him,<note n="o" place="margin">Ruth. 2.20.</note> 
               <hi>Not ceaſing to doe good to the liuing and to the dead,</hi> for his ſake to his wife and children. Of which you reaped a plentifull and timely harueſt of ioy and comfort, though it is your griefe to liue to ſee his autumne and fall.<note n="p" place="margin">Iob 2.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0.</note> 
               <hi>Muſt we receiue good at the hand of God,
<pb facs="tcp:18375:12"/> and not receiue euill?</hi> But yet giue leaue to adde (<note n="q" place="margin">Iob 32.22.</note> 
               <hi>For I may not giue titles, leſt my maker ſhould take me away ſuddenly</hi>) as <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard</hi> in another caſe;<note n="r" place="margin">Deus exhon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rans, on erat Ber.</note> 
               <hi>When God doth vnburden vs, he doth burden vs:</hi> So God ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing vnburdened you of that griefe and ſorrow, of that infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie &amp; reproch which many mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thers and ſiſters haue, &amp; to to many of your rank, while theirs liue lice<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiouſly, <hi>reprobate to euery good work,</hi> diſhonou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Chriſt Ieſus whom they profeſſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and their kindered from which they did proceed. I ſay while God hath vnbur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dened you of this, and honored you with the contrary, he doth
<pb facs="tcp:18375:12"/> onerate and burden you with the dutie of thankefulnes, which among other duties is this, that you continue with a godly zeale and Chriſtian care to imitate and emulate the worthy graces and practiſe of godlines which were in this your honour &amp; crowne, which is worthily eſteemed in him, and will be in you, the higheſt matter of your honour and praiſe. Diuines giue the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of it to be this, becauſe by pietie and holines of life wee aſcend,<note n="ſ" place="margin">Ad primarium illud bonum vnde originem traximus Nazian. orat. <hi>33.</hi> in land. Hiero.</note> 
               <hi>to the firſt and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mary good whence we had our beginning.</hi> And in the Apoſtles phraſe it is to<note n="t" place="margin">2 Pet. 1.4.</note> 
               <hi>Be partakers of the godly na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</hi> Seeing we are the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration
<pb facs="tcp:18375:13"/> of God, made to his i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, what greater glory ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we haue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to preſerue that image &amp; be like vnto him to whoſe ſimilitude wee were made, for as one ſaith,<note n="u" place="margin">Vna nobilitas imitatio dei.</note> 
               <hi>There is no ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to the imitation of God:</hi> which is then performed when we imitate thoſe who haue walked with God. The Heathen man ſaith,<note n="x" place="margin">Vt quiſe co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munt adhibent ſpeculum, ſic ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturus negotium proponit ſibi lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datorum virorum exempla. Plutar.</note> 
               <hi>That as they who dreſſe themſelues vſe glaſſes, ſo thoſe who are to performe any thing, propound to themſelues the examples of praiſe-worthy men.</hi> You honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Ladies haue a moſt true, and (as I may ſo ſpeake) a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall glaſſe to ſee to addreſſe your ſelues to goodnes by, euen
<pb facs="tcp:18375:13"/> the life of your worthy, it is that which will ſooner checke you then any, as it ought to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect you more then any<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> nay it is that by which others will ſooner reprehend your ſtepping aſide and ſtraying. I humbly beſeech you therefore (giue me leaue to further your forward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes) walke after his waies &amp; runne with good reſolution the race of pietie and true godlines he hath finiſhed before you, of whom I may ſay as <hi>Ambroſe</hi> of <hi>Abraham,</hi>
               <note n="y" place="margin">Mortuus eſt imbona ſenecture, eo quod in bonitate propoſiti perman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit.</note> 
               <hi>He died in a good age, for why? he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeuerd in his good reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions euen vnto the end,</hi> and now enioieth the crowne of life.</p>
            <p>And ſo I humbly and hartily
<pb facs="tcp:18375:14"/> commend you all to the grace of God which is able to build you further, &amp; giue an inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance among them who are ſanctified by faith in Chriſt Ieſus and ſo I reſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your in all humble manner, RICHARD STOCKE</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:18375:14"/>
            <head>¶ To the Chriſtian READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reader who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer thou art, whether one that was an auditor of this ſermon, or one that otherwiſe knowes me and my practiſe in this kind of funerall duties, If thou he of the firſt ſort be informed, that in the ſermon thou ſhalt find ſome few things ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded not to the ſubſtance, but to the amplification of ſome vſe, which I could not for the ſtraightnes of time deliuer. In the commendations of this moſt commendable Noble thou ſhalt find ſome few things ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, which ſlipped out of my memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry at the time when I deliuered it, but not many; and the like number added which came to my knowledge
<pb facs="tcp:18375:15"/> ſince. At alſo one thing diſplaced, namely his meditations vpon his ſermons in the morning, which he did after dinner. I aſſure thee I haue ſet downe nothing, as I deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red nothing, but the true and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall grounds of euery particular, I knew my ſelfe; diuers particulars I receiued of others who are iudici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, honeſt, &amp; religious, agreeing al with the grounds of my own know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, &amp; ſo as I had grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to beleeue them, I knew nothing why I might not then, and now communicate them to thee, whereby I may profit thee by the bleſsing of God more, then my praiſe can honor him. But if thou art one of the ſecond ſort, knowing my vſe to he very ſparing in praiſing of the dead, and ſo may wonder I ſhould be ſo plentifull in the commendations of this honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble gentleman, know, I neuer had ſuch a ſubiect to ſpeake of, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thou reſpect nature or grace, his earthly or heauenly condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:18375:15"/>
            <p>For this cauſe I haue bin the more large, and ſpecially becauſe he was a publike perſon, more eies were vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, and well they might be, for hee was not ſo eminent in place as he was in grace, for his gifts and graces &amp; power of religion were ſo excellent and rare, as I neuer yet knew in any, whom I had occaſion to ſpeake of I wiſh I might hereafter meet with ſome like him, but I haue little hope, though I do not deſpaire. If I find any deſeruing as he did, I will not leſſen their worthineſſe nor darken their light, ſpecially if they be publike perſons. Yet me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> muſt giue me leaue in all things, to goe vpon my owne grounds, and not tie me to their conceits. Affection of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten blindeth thoſe who are ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally linked together, when it can not deceiue other;, who are a far of: often when friends highly thinke of their friends eſtate, the phyſition diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerneth better of their condition, and finds both ſpirits and bloud tainted, when they thinke they are
<pb facs="tcp:18375:16"/> in good health. I would willingly ſet forth true golden veſsels to the view of the world, but I haue no affection to gild potſheards. If I know mens liues I can the better iudge of their deaths, if I knew they haue liued well, I ſhall be better perſwaded of their deaths: if euill, I ſhall be made to doubt much, of that, though it be ſeemingly good, yet <hi>I</hi> had rather thinke charitably then ſpeake confidently. In this kind if I ſpeake ſparingly I pray men <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> blame thoſe who giue me no more ground, and not to reproue me, that dare not be ſo bold as ſome others, I will adde no more, neither will I longer detaine thee, gentle rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, from Gods word of life and death, nor from the life and death of this worthy noble. I pray God giue thee as much good by them, as I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to thee, to thy heart and life, and ſo farewell.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine in the Lord Ieſus, RICHARD STOCKE.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:18375:16"/>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:18375:17"/>
            <head>Faults eſcaped in Printing.</head>
            <p>Pag. 19. line. 14. vrbilius, r. vrbicius p. 44. l. 1. County, r. country. p. 47. l. 14. take out he. p. 47. l. 15. r. he only. p. 54. l. 4. im. r. him. p. 85. l. 25 ſeruants r. ſermons. p. 86 l. 4 that vpon. r. that as vpon p. 93. l. 10. beauties r. beautie.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>In the margent.</head>
               <p>Pag. <hi>3.</hi> Ier. r. ſerm p. <hi>22.</hi> etiam r. Baſil. p. <hi>33.</hi> voluiſſe, r. Dei voluiſſe. p <hi>35.</hi> &amp;c. r. ex. p. <hi>42.</hi> vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuticu, r. viaticu. p. <hi>46.</hi> ledere, r. ludere. p. <hi>53.</hi> trahence, r. trabente. ibid pretioſum. r. pretio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſam. p. <hi>90.</hi> vites. r. viles. p. <hi>93</hi> et fi, r. et ſi.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:18375:17"/>
            <head>A Sermon PREACHED AT THE Funerall of the Lord HARINGTON.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>MICAH 7.1, 2.</bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Woe is me, for I am as the Summer gatherings, and as the grapes of the vintage: there is no cluſter to eate: my ſoule deſireth the firſt ripe fruits.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The good man is periſhed out of the earth, and there is none righteous among men.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He elect veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell and holy Apoſtle both for <hi>Iewes</hi> and <hi>Gentiles</hi> Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> telleth the <hi>Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> and in them the whole
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:18375:18"/> Church, that they were<note n="a" place="margin">1. Cor. 3.9.</note> 
               <hi>Gods hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sbandary;</hi> whence it will follow, and out of relation, that the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter is Gods Husbandman. Now the ſecular husbandman hath and obſerueth his ſeaſons to ſow his ſeed, and his ground to caſt his corne into, as hee ſoweth ſome in the Autumne and fall of the leaſe, ſome in winter and dead time of the yeere, ſome in the ſpring and renewing of the yeere, ſome in a dry ſeaſon, and ſome in a wet; ſome in a moiſt clay, and ſome in a dry ſandy ground: and as the holy Ghoſt ſpeaketh,<note n="b" place="margin">Eſay 38 25, 26</note> 
               <hi>Hee ſoweth the fetches, and cummin, and caſteth in wheat by meaſure, and the appointed barley and rye in their pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</hi> And all this, <hi>for his God doth inſtruct him to haue diſcretion, and doth teach him.</hi> As the ſecular, ſo the ſpirituall husbandman hath his ſeed for all ſeaſons, and for all grounds, all hearts: ſome for the time of mercy and iudgement, for the ſeaſon of mirth &amp; mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:18375:18"/> as wet and dry ſeaſons: ſome for the birth &amp; buriall, as for the ſpring and fall: ſome for them who ſorrow in <hi>Sion,</hi> and ſome for them that reioice in <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and as <hi>Eſay</hi> ſpeakes,<note n="c" place="margin">Eſay 61.2.</note> 
               <hi>to preach the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable yeere of the Lord, and the day of vengeance of our God, and to comfort all that mourne.</hi> And all this, becauſe <hi>his God doth inſtruct him to haue diſcretion, and doth teach him.</hi> And as the ſame Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet ſaith,<note n="d" place="margin">Eſay 28.29.</note> 
               <hi>This alſo commeth from the Lord of hoſts, which is wonderful in counſell, and excellent in works.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now to allude to the words of Saint <hi>Paul,</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">1. Corinth. 3.10.</note> 
               <hi>According to the grace of God which is giuen to me, as a skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full maſter builder, &amp;c.</hi> As <hi>Bernard</hi> ſpeakes of himſelfe, ſo I of my ſelfe,<note n="f" place="margin">Non ſum Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheta, non ſum Apoſtolus: &amp; Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetae tamen &amp; Apoſtoli (audeo dicere) vice fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>: &amp; quibus non equor meritis, eorum impli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or curis. ſuper Cant. Ier. <hi>46.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>I am no Apoſtle: and yet</hi> (I may be bold to ſay) <hi>I am in ſtead of a Prophet, of an Apoſtle, I ſupply the place, and ſerue in the turne of a Prophet and an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, and though I am inferior to them in fitnes and abilitie, yet I
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:18375:19"/> am incumbred with the ſame cares.</hi> I ſay then, according to the grace of God giuen me, as a skilfull huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandman in my meaſure, I haue thought this portion, and this meaſure of the eternall ſeed of God, fitting this ſeaſon: ſeed of ſorrow for a ſeaſon of ſorrow, and a portion of Scripture containing leſſons of lamentation for an Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditory, which I know well are, (as they haue iuſt cauſe) full of la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation.</p>
            <p>This Chapter brancheth and diuideth it ſelfe naturally, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any violence into two princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall parts. The firſt is a lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Prophet and the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, from the firſt verſe to the eight. The ſecond is a conſolation to the Church and faithfull, from the eight verſe to the end of the Chapter. In the lamentation are two things laid downe: The thing which they lament for and bewaile, in the 1. 2. 3. 4. 5. and 6. verſes. And a counſell and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:18375:19"/> to the godly, how to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meane and carry themſelues with ſome good wiſdome and profit a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt thoſe euils lamented for, &amp; that in the 5. &amp; 7. verſes. The things lamented for are of two ſorts: Firſt, the paucity and great defect of the good: Secondly, the plurality and great abundance of the wicked. The firſt conteined in my text, is ſet downe firſt vnder a Parable and ſimilitude, which helps both preſent attention, and future memory, being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightfull: Secondly, plainely, and without parable, which truely enformeth the iudgement, being perſpicuous.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Woe is me.]</hi> As if he had ſaid,<note place="margin">The meaning.</note> how hard is my caſe? how heauy is Gods hand vpon me? how mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable is my condition, that haue now ſo few holy, good, &amp; righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous men remaining in mee, who haue formerly abounded with good men of all ſorts and rankes? I that haue beene as a field full
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:18375:20"/> fraught with Corne, as a Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard abounding with beautifull bunches of Grapes, am now de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute, and depriued of theſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all gathered from me to their Fathers, and the Father of all ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits:<note n="f" place="margin">Ruth. 1.20, 21.</note> 
               <hi>Woe is me. Call me not</hi> Naomi, <hi>but call me</hi> Mara: for the Almighty hath giuen me much bitterneſſe. I was ful, but the Lord hath made me empty: <hi>Why call ye me</hi> Naomi, <hi>ſeeing the Lord hath humbled mee?</hi> and <hi>the Almighty hath brought me into aduerſitie,</hi> as <hi>Naomi</hi> ſpeakes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I am as the ſummer gatherings, &amp; as the grapes of the vintage.]</hi> To paſſe by many interpretations of theſe words, which breed confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion rather then vnderſtanding: <hi>Hieroms</hi> reading of them I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue fully and naturally to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe them.<note n="g" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ra factus ſum ſicut qui co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ligit in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>de m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. Hie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>For I am as he that gathereth in harueſt the Grapes of the vintage.</hi> For hauing ſaid that he was as hee that gathereth in Summer, and not expreſſing what hee gathereth, hee addeth, <hi>the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:18375:20"/> grapes of the vintage.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>There is no cluſter to eate.]</hi> And it is with me as it is with him; that as hee found not a cluſter of grapes, all being gone before hee came, that he could finde none to refreſh himſelf; ſo not I one good man to comfort my ſelfe withall.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>My ſoule deſireth the firſt ripe fruits.]</hi> To paſſe here alſo by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers interpretations as not profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to bee ſtood vpon, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue it to be as if hee had ſaid: I am as he that gathereth Grapes, and findeth none, deſireth that he might but haue the firſt ripe fruits: when all ſhould be ripe in the time of Harueſt, I wiſh I could finde but a few like thoſe that are firſt ripe before others, but I find none of them at all.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The good man is periſhed out of the earth.]</hi> The Prophet here ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaineth the parable, and ſetteth downe in plaine termes that hee did before in ſimilitude, &amp; ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that there are but few good
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:18375:21"/> men left in the Land &amp; Church, which hee proueth, becauſe the Lord had gathered many good men in peace to their fathers, and taken them away. The word tranſlated here, <hi>good man,</hi> is by ſome read, the <hi>mercifull man,</hi> and then they take it either actiuely, one that ſheweth mercy &amp; good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to others; or paſsiuely, one that God hath ſhewed mercy and goodnes to: this is the cauſe of that, man being merciful, becauſe hee hath found mercy. <hi>Hierome</hi> readeth it <hi>ſanctus,</hi> as it were, one whom God hath ſanctified, and of his grace conſecrated to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. The Septuagints reade it <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: that is, <hi>reuerens &amp; religio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus; a deuout, reuerent,</hi> and <hi>religious man:</hi> they are all to one purpoſe, and in deed the ſame. Now the Prophet bewaileth the taking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way of ſuch: for though he ſaith, <hi>he periſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th,</hi> yet hee meaneth not ſimply that they were periſhed; but as <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> of one,<note n="h" place="margin">Dormuit, non mortuus eſt: qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſcit, non perijt. Chriſ. hom. <hi>69</hi> ad p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p. Ant.</note> 
               <hi>Hee
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:18375:21"/> ſleepeth, he is not dead; he reſteth, hee is not periſhed:</hi> ſo heere of theſe, they ſleep, and are not dead; they are at reſt, and are not periſhed: for the Prophet ſpeaketh out of the opinion of the wicked, who were fixed, as it were, in the world, and had there their felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and ſo iudged them to be pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed, who were taken out of the world ſomewhat vntimely, and vnſeaſonably, as it ſeemed to their ſence and iudgement.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>There is none righteous.]</hi> By this the Prophet telleth, how many are gathered from among men, not a few, but many, euen ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, that none remaineth: he mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, in compariſon, not ſimply none, but as it is vſed, <hi>none</hi> for very few, and in compariſon of the great multitude none; as in the <hi>Pſalme,</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Pſal. 14.3.</note> 
               <hi>All are gone out of the way; they are all corrupt, there is none that doth good, no not one.</hi> Heere <hi>all</hi> is put for the moſt, and <hi>none</hi> for the feweſt, and in compariſon none.
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:18375:22"/> and as in the <hi>Philippians,</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Philip. 2.21.</note> 
               <hi>All ſeeke their owne, and not that which is Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſts.</hi> By righteous man, he meaneth the vpright man, which walketh vprightly with God and man, and turneth not to the right hand, nor to the left; one that ſheweth his holines by his vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right and iuſt dealing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith,<note n="l" place="margin">Pro. 23.1.</note> 
               <hi>When thou ſitteſt to eate with a Ruler, conſider dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently what is before thee:</hi> Which words <hi>Bernard</hi> tranſlateth from corporall to ſpirituall foode, and feaſting, from a table to a text, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> diſhes to doctrines, &amp; ſaith to the hearer,<note n="m" place="margin">Int<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>mini pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentem menſam, quomodo ſupernis eſt refert<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> delicijs ſpiritualia ſunt, et diuina, quae nobis in ra appo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>untur. Bernard: ſuper Cant<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſerm<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>29.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Behold the preſent ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, how it is furniſhed with delights from aboue: they are ſpirituall, and diuine, which are therein ſet before vs.</hi> And to the teacher:<note n="n" place="margin">Diligenter conſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dera quae tibi ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ntur, quia ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia te oportet prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parare. Ibidem.</note> 
               <hi>Conſider diligently what things are ſet before thee,</hi> knowing <hi>that ſuch alſo thou oughteſt to prepare:</hi> that hee take his doctrines from the text, and not bring them to it: carue them of the things vppon the table,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:18375:22"/> not fetching things elſewhere.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Honorable,</hi> and <hi>beloued,</hi> behold this table, ſee how it is furniſhed with ſpirituall diſhes: and I for my part will conſider them, and not propoſe all, ſo much as to your ſight, or taſte, but will onely labour to feede you with ſome two or three which are moſt fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting our preſent occaſion, and your prepared appetites. The firſt whereof is this.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine </seg>1</label> The ſcarcitie and paucitie, the decay and the defect of holy and good men hath euer beene eſteemed ſufficient and moſt iuſt cauſe of mourning and lamentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by them who ſuruiued them and liued after them, being good men, led and guided by Gods ſpirit. Thus the Prophet and the godly of his time thought it worth their ſighes &amp; teares, that ſo many of the righteous men were gone, and ſo few remained in the Church. Thus and this did <hi>Dauid</hi> by the ſpirit of God la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:18375:23"/> 
               <note n="o" place="margin">Pſal. 12.1.</note> 
               <hi>Help Lord, for there is not a godly man left, for the righteous are failed among the children of men.</hi> Thus the Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> bewaileth when hee had propheſied how few there ſhould be remaining that were good,<note n="p" place="margin">Eſay 24.13.</note> 
               <hi>As the ſhaking of an Oliue tree &amp; as the grapes whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the vintage is ended.</hi> After he expreſſeth his ſorrow;<note n="q" place="margin">verſe. 16.</note> 
               <hi>My leanenes, my leane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes; woe is me.</hi> Thus certaine men fearing God, made great<note n="r" place="margin">Acts 8.5.</note> 
               <hi>lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations for Stephen,</hi> that the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the good was leſſened but by one. This may ſhew that vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly they lamented the death &amp; decay of good men, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they<note n="ſ" place="margin">Acts 21.10.11.12 13.</note> wept ſo greatly for the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of <hi>Paul,</hi> propheſied by <hi>Agabus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And why thinke we this to be matter of lamentations? <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>1</label> Firſt, becauſe by this meanes the Church &amp; the land is exceeding<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly weakned, and vnarmed: for not one of them but they are in their ranke (as <hi>Ioaſh</hi> the King lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſicke <hi>Eliſha,</hi> and weeping vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:18375:23"/> his face ſaid,)<note n="t" place="margin">2. Kings 13.14.</note> 
               <hi>The Charet of Iſrael, and the horſemen of the ſame:</hi> not for their perſons, who are men inferiour to many others, not for their pollicie, which are of inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our reach then many thouſands, but for their pietie and praiers:<note n="u" place="margin">Iob 22.30.</note> 
               <hi>For the innocent ſhall deliuer the Iland, and it ſhall be preſerued by the purenes of his hands.</hi> And as <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome</hi> ſaith:<note n="x" place="margin">Vt ciuitas non cincta muris facile venit in poteſtatem hoſtium ſic &amp; ani<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ma non munita precibus. Chriſ. de precat. lib. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>As a Citie not compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with walles, eaſily cometh into the power of the enemie, ſo the ſoule not fenced with praiers:</hi> ſo on the contrary; the walles of the Citie are the praiers of the ſaints, or at leaſt they vphold the wals. As<note n="y" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioſh.</hi> 6.20.</note> at the ſhoutings of the people, <hi>the walles of Ierico fel downe,</hi> ſo at the prayers &amp; cries of the godly, the walles of the Church and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey ſtand vp. Theſe are the ſtrength of their ſtrength.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>2</label> Secondly, becauſe this is a fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runner, and certaine immediate ſigne &amp; prediction of ſome feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full iudgement &amp; plague of God
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:18375:24"/> at hand ready to breake in vpon them, as the red &amp; lowring skie in the morning, is a ſigne of a ſhortly enſuing tempeſt: ſo the taking of theſe away of an imminent plague, the Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> giues this reaſon of it:<note n="z" place="margin">Eſay 57.1.</note> 
               <hi>The righteous pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſheth, and no man conſidereth it in heart, and mercifull men are taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, and no man vnderſtandeth that the righteous is taken away from the euill to come:</hi> Their taking away, doth then directly preſage an euil to come? for as the Apoſtle ſaith in an other caſe, ſo I in this,<note n="a" place="margin">2. Theſſal. 2.7.</note> 
               <hi>Only he which now with-holdeth ſhall let, till he be taken out of the way:</hi> theſe while they are, with-hold and keepe backe the plague. As the Angel ſaid to <hi>Lot,</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Geneſ. 19.22.</note> 
               <hi>I can do nothing till thou be come thither,</hi> namely to bring the plague vppon <hi>Sodome</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah,</hi> but he no ſooner was entred into <hi>Zoar,</hi> but inſtantly the Lord raigned fire and brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone vpon <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah.</hi> As <hi>Noah</hi> was no ſooner in the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:18375:24"/> Arke,<note n="c" place="margin">Gen. 7.11.13.</note> 
               <hi>but in the very ſelfe ſame day were all the fountaines of the deepe broken vp, and the win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes of heauen were opened.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>1</label> Now to make ſome vſe of this point to our ſelues. Firſt how farre are they then from the ſpirit of the Prophet and holy men? what enemies to their owne ſtrength &amp; defence, what furtherers of their owne plagues? who wiſh and deſire, who worke and procure the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay &amp; diminution of the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the godly and faithfull? who account it matter of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging rather then ſorrow, of laughing then lamentation, to heare of their fall and taking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way: As <hi>Saluian</hi> ſaid of ſome in his time:<note n="d" place="margin">An credimus forte quod Capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus populus ille no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fuerit, qui laetus tunc in ſuorum captiuitatibus fuit? Captinus cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de et ſenſu non erat qui inter ſuorum ſupplicia ridebat, qui iugulari ſe in ſuorum iugulis non intelligebat, qui m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt in ſuorum mortibus non put<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat? Salutanu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> de Guber. De li. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Doe wee beleeue that that people was not captiuated in minde, who were glad at the capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uity of their owne people; that they were not captiuated both in heart and feeling, that laughed at the puniſhment of theirs, who vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:18375:25"/> not that in their ſlaughter they themſelues were ſlaine, who thought not that in their deaths they themſelues died?</hi> In the ſame manner may I ſpeake of theſe: doe wee not thinke that theſe are captiuated in their mindes, who thus ioy in their dangers? are they not miſerable, &amp; blind, and benummed, who thus laugh in their perils? who vnderſtand not, that by this they are as <hi>Samſon</hi> was, ſhorne of his haire, &amp; ſo depriued of their ſtrength; who thinke not that by this they take away thoſe that keepe backe the iudgements of God, &amp; make way if they may haue their wills, that they may the ſooner &amp; more ſeuerely breake in vpon them? And this whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they doe it, as <hi>Cain</hi> hated and ſlew his brother, and for that cauſe as St. <hi>Iohn</hi> ſpeaketh.<note n="e" place="margin">1. Iohn 3.12.</note> 
               <hi>Becauſe his owne workes were euill, &amp; his brothers good;</hi> becauſe they take themſelues withall
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:18375:25"/> reproue by their carriage, more then by their words.<note n="f" place="margin">Efficacius loqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur vox operis, quam ſermonis. Bern.</note> 
               <hi>For the voice of deeds ſpeake more effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally then the voice of words:</hi> as <hi>Bernard</hi> ſaith. Whether a man teach or reproue, and ſo hate them for this, and not without cauſe. For (as <hi>Saluian</hi> ſpeakes)<note n="g" place="margin">Nam quis dicere poſſit, quod ſine cauſa, homines ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licot omnibus a ſe vitae ac morum ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dijs diſcrepantes, in quibus nihil vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant ſuum quoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am dei totu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ima enim cauſa eſt diſcordiarum diuerſitas volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum: quia fieri aut omnino non poteſt, aut vix poteſt, vt eam rem in alio quiſquam diligit, a qua ipſe diſſentit. Itaque eos non ſine cauſa (vt dixi) oderunt, in quibus omnia ſibi aemula atque ini<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ica cernebant. Saluian lib. <hi>8.</hi> de Gub. Dei.</note> 
               <hi>Who can ſay that it is without cauſe, being me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> altogether different in their life and manners, in whom they ſaw nothing that was theirs, becauſe the whole was Gods: for the greateſt cauſe of diſcord is the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſity of wils: becauſe it either cannot be at all, or ſcarce be, that any ſhould loue that thing in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, from which he himſelfe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenteth: therefore</hi> (as I ſaid) <hi>they hated them not without cauſe, in whom they ſaw all things repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to themſelues.</hi> Whether it be for this, or it be for the truths ſake which they profeſſe, hold, and defend, as the ſeed and brood of <hi>Anti-Chriſt</hi> euer did the Church of God, or for any
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:18375:26"/> other thing, yet doe they no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more then depriue them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues of their ſafety and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, lay themſelues open to the plagues and iudgements of God, though they benefit and aduantage the faithfull: for as <hi>Euſebius</hi> ſpeakes in the life of <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> but of that which hapned in the daies of <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> his father, that the <hi>Emperors</hi> did ſo perſecute the godly,<note n="h" place="margin">Vſque eo, vti bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ui imperatorum regiae ſanctis vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is eſſent omnino or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batae: quae res au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thores maleficij clementi dei obtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu, &amp; curatione prorſus priuauit, quippè qui dum homines pios in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecturentur, etiam corum preces inſec<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tati ſunt, &amp; a ſe peuitus a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erterunt Euſeb. in vit. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant. l. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>that in a ſhort time the palaces of the Emperors were deſtitute of all good men: which thing</hi> (as hee ſaith) <hi>did altogether depriue the Authors of this wickednes, of the fauorable countenance, care, and regard of God, for while they did perſecute godly men, they alſo perſecuted their praiers, and ſo altogether turned them from them.</hi> So is it with theſe, and ſo will it be with thoſe who thus hate and ſeeke to remoue <hi>the godly and faithfull,</hi> that as <hi>Iuſtin Martyr</hi> ſpake to <hi>Antonius Pius</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:18375:26"/> in his ſecond Apologie for the Chriſtians.<note n="i" place="margin">Vt in delatores ipſos animaduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis, min<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>me peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus: ſufficit enim ipſis ſua maligni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas, &amp; bonarum rerum ignoratio. Iuſt. Mart. Apol. <hi>2.</hi> pro Chriſtianis.</note> 
               <hi>We deſire not that ye puniſh the accuſers, for their owne malignitie, and ignorance of good things is enough for them:</hi> So may we ſay; no neede to pray for vengeance vppon the haters &amp; perſecuters of the godly and faithfull, for their own wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes is enough to bring Gods iudgements vpon them, their ignorance of good things, to bring euill enough vpon their backes, when by this they bring much good to the godly: for as <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaith,<note n="k" place="margin">In <hi>Pſal. 93.</hi> Illi qui martyres perſecutiſunt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequendo in terra, in caelum mittebant &amp; ſcientes quidem praeſentis vitae dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num infe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rebant, ſed neſcientes futu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rae vitae lucrum conferebant.</note> 
               <hi>They which perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted the martyrs, in perſecuting them on earth, they ſent the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, &amp; whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wittingly they infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the loſſe of this preſent life, vnwittingly they conferred vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the gain of the life to come<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> yea as <hi>Euſeb. reporteth the ſpeech of</hi> Lucius <hi>to</hi> Vrbilius <hi>the Gouernor condemned for ſpeaking againſt his ſentence which hee gaue againſt Chriſtians, and profeſſing himſelfe
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:18375:27"/> vpon, interogation to be a Chriſtian he confeſſed,</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Permagnam ſe debere gratiam profitebatur, nam ita ſe non iniqui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſolum &amp; improbis eiuſmodi dominis liberatu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſore dix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it, ſed etiam ad bonum patrem, et clementem regem d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um recte pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecturum. Euſeb. Hiſt lib. <hi>4.</hi> cap. <hi>16.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>That hee did owe great thankes, for ſo</hi> (he ſaid) <hi>hee ſhould be not onely free from thoſe wicked Lords, but alſo ſhould goe directly vnto God the father of goodnes, and King of mercy and clemency:</hi> And theſe gone, then nothing but plagues remaineth for the other; nay whether they be gone, or abide ſtil among the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, they are but a curſe to the wicked world, not but that they might haue a bleſſing by them, and haue more then they ſee or acknowledge, nor that they are the cauſe of euil to them, but the occaſion, becauſe of their hatred and handling of them, for while they euilly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat them, liuing with them, and will not let them freely ſerue their God, neither with them, nor ſeperate from them, as <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and the <hi>Aegiptians</hi> would not ſuffer <hi>Iſrael:</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore like <hi>Egipt</hi> are they plagued
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:18375:27"/> with ſundry iudgements for abuſing of them, though by their praiers many are turned and kept from them. And when they are taken from them, more heauie plagues doe abide them, and will come in vppon them: For as <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſaith,<note n="m" place="margin">Egredientibus Iſraelitis de Aegip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, exterminata eſt Aegiptus, ſic &amp; ſancti cum de iſto mundo defecerint, caſurus eſt iſte mundus. Chriſoſt. in Mat. <hi>1.</hi> Hom. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>As the Iſraelites going cut of Egipt, Egipt was deſtroyed, ſo when the godly ſhall be quite departed out of the world, the world ſhall be deſtroyed.</hi> This conſidered, they haue no cauſe to hate them liuing, and wiſh to be rid of them, much leſſe to procure their departing: but much cauſe haue they to ſorrow and grieue when they are taken from them. And therefore much are they blin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with malice, that they can wiſh their fall, and reioyce and laugh at the time of their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture, and willingly, and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully thruſt them out of the world, as the <hi>Egiptians</hi> did <hi>Iſrael</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>2</label> Secondly, it is then manifeſted
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:18375:28"/> to be a heauie curſe &amp; fearefull iudgement to a Land, to a Church, when men of piety &amp; religion, faithfull and godly men are taken away; why elſe do the ſuruiuing godly mourne and bewaile them, when there is no band of nature, no worldly or ciuill reſpect that wrings teares and ſorrow from them, but meerely becauſe ſuch are taken away. They were neither fooles nor children to weepe for trifles, and things wherein there was no loſſe. When they wept, and wept bitterly with great lamentations and mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, the cauſe muſt certainely be either their ſin, or elſe ſome great iudgement, either priua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue or poſitiue. The taking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way of the godly, eſpecially by an ordinary hand of God can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſinne, but a puniſhment for ſinne, and that which is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted to be a very fearefull one. Then muſt we, then ought
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:18375:28"/> we to ſigh and grone, to ſorrow and mourne vnder this, as a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry heauie iudgement: wee ſhall performe herein no vnfitting, thing, nothing vnworthy of vs, whatſoeuer we be, or whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer we be; it is fitting the moſt holieſt, when <hi>Eſay</hi> the Prophet, and other of the faithfull haue done it: it is fitting the moſt honourable, whenas <hi>Dauid</hi> the King, and <hi>Eſay</hi> of the blood royall haue done it, &amp; thought themſelues to haue calling to it and cauſe enough when ſuch things befell the time they li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in. We are all (honourable and beloued) called to mourne; for how many men of note for pietie and holineſſe, for religion and vprightnes, whom God had ſpecially endued with grace and goodnes, and annointed them with this oyle aboue their fellowes, and men of their ranke and faſhion, how many of theſe are taken, and remoued from
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:18375:29"/> vs within theſe few yeares, wee being altogether vnworthy of them, &amp; he hauing made them<note n="h" place="margin">Reu. 3.4.</note> 
               <hi>worthy</hi> (as it is ſaid of a few in the Church of <hi>Sardie) that is fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting for himſelfe.</hi> And while wee inioied them, we proſpered by their preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; praiers, we were bleſſed for them; for their ſakes, at their ſuites were many iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments turned fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs, that other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe would haue fallen vpon vs, as <hi>Moſes</hi> by his praiers tied the Lords hand that hee could not hurt <hi>Iſrael:</hi> as for <hi>Ioſeph</hi> not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Potiphar</hi> fared the better, but for his, &amp; the familie of <hi>Iacob, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gipt</hi> proſpered, &amp; was preſerued when other countries periſhed with famin in the time of want. Doubtles as <hi>Eliſha</hi> ſaid to <hi>Ieho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram,</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">2. Kings. 3.14.</note> 
               <hi>If it were not that I regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the preſence of</hi> Iehoſhaphat <hi>King of</hi> Iuda, <hi>I would not haue looked towards thee, nor ſeene thee:</hi> ſo if it had not beene for their preſence &amp; praiers, God would
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:18375:29"/> neuer haue reſpected our ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and our generals to haue giuen them ſuch reliefe as they found, when they were often in diſtreſſe in <hi>Ireland,</hi> &amp; elſewhere. As <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſaith, that<note n="k" place="margin">M. Aurel. germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicam ſitm Chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tianorum fortè mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litum precationi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus impetrato im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bri diſcuſſam con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtatur. Tertul. aduer. Gent. Apol.</note> 
               <hi>M. Aurelius</hi> the Emperor, when he was in fight againſt the <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,</hi> and in a ſtreight for wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; <hi>by his letters witneſſed, that the German thirſt was driuen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with aſhower, obtained by the praiers of the Chriſtian ſouldiers:</hi> So may I ſay, that from many ſtreights, haue wee and our armies obtained reliefe by them. Yea as <hi>Moſes</hi> and his praier ouercame more then <hi>Ioſhua</hi> and his power and ſtrength: for<note n="l" place="margin">Exod. 11.11.</note> 
               <hi>when Moſes held vp his hand, Iſrael preuailed:</hi> that is, when he praied feruently, <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> had the day of the <hi>Amale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kites,</hi> but when <hi>he let his hands down,</hi> Amalek <hi>preuailed:</hi> that is, when he left praying, the enemy got the better.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:18375:30"/>
            <p>So may wee ſay of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of the land, that at all times their ſuites to God when they were feruent, preuailed more then the ſwords of our Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines and ſouldiers; their prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers were of more force then all their peeces, their cries, then all the Cannons of the Armie:<note n="m" place="margin">Heb. 11.34.</note> by their faith were turned to flight the armies of the <hi>Aliants.</hi> But now when ſo many of theſe are taken away, when they haue yeelded to nature, and are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued into glory, haue we not cauſe to mourne with great la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentations? Yes, yes, if wee did vnderſtand thoſe things that did belong to our peace, and ſafety, if we did conceiue right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of things tending to our woe, and miſery; if we doe not, if we cannot, it is becauſe, as <hi>Saluian</hi> ſaith to the Catholike Church,<note n="n" place="margin">Repugnante con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra temetipſum tua foelicitate. Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uian. l. <hi>1.</hi> ad Eccleſ. Catholiam.</note> 
               <hi>Thy owne felicitie fighteth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thy ſelfe:</hi> our proſperity, our plenty ſtandeth againſt vs,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:18375:30"/> and hath bewitched vs, wee are ſo drunke with the pleaſures thereof, that as drunken men we ſee no danger, though we lie open to infinite danger hereby. Shall vſe that of <hi>Saluian?</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">Ablâtus erat a peccatoribus timor ne poſſet eſſe cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tela. Saluian. de</note> 
               <hi>Feare was taken away from offenders, that there ſhould be no caution a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it.</hi> We are deſtitute of the feare of euill, becauſe we ſhould not take care to auoid it, and that it ſhould come vpon vs vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>awares: God forbid, God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid, let me be found a falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet. But to draw to an end of this point <hi>(Honorable and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued)</hi> had the old world cauſe to feare and mourne when <hi>Noah</hi> went into the Arke? was it high time for <hi>Sodom</hi> to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment when <hi>Lot</hi> was taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, and haſtened out of it by the Angell? and haue not wee cauſe? can we not mourne when ſo many <hi>Noahs</hi> &amp; <hi>Lots</hi> (I wrong none, as I take it, though I ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour ſome by this compariſon)
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:18375:31"/> are taken away? and haſtened away out of our Land &amp; Cities? Truſt me now, or time will come when you ſhall truſt me, that we haue cauſe and cauſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine to lament and mourne, not for them who dying in the Lord, are happy with the Lord, &amp; reſt from all their labours and miſeries; but as Chriſt ſaid to the women that followed him, <hi>Weepe not for mee, but for your ſelues and your children:</hi> ſo wee for our ſelues and our children: for hauing been ſafe by them, and ſtrengthened through them, they are taken away from the plague, we lie open to it, and it haſtneth the faſter, becauſe they that kept it from vs, are remoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. Men vſe to fence and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend, to keepe watch and ward ouer their corne fields, whiles the corne and fruits are in them vnreaped, vngathered: when they are gathered, and put ſafe
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:18375:31"/> into the barne, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is open tide, as they ſay, they lay them open to beaſts of all kind, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time ſet fire on the ſtubble. So, and ſo hath God dealt oft times with many lands and countries, wherein his Church and the godly haue liued. And are we better then they? Nay as <hi>Saluian</hi> ſaith,<note n="p" place="margin">Deteriores ſumus quia meliores eſſe debemus. Saluian.</note> 
               <hi>We are worſe, becauſe wee ſhould be better:</hi> hauing ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples to admoniſh vs: haue we any priuiledge or prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction more then they? nay, nay, we haue no helpe, vnleſſe wee ceaſe to doe euill and learne to doe well, and labour to bee good and faithfull as they were, and beleeuing this to bee true, it may be, (as <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſpeaketh in one place:<note n="q" place="margin">Fides facit for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midinem, ſormid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſolicitudinem. Ter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tull.</note> 
               <hi>faith cauſeth feare, feare carefulneſſe:</hi>) ſo our faith may breed feare, and our feare care to ceaſe to be euill, and learne to doe well, that repenting for our ſinnes, and practiſing true piete, we
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:18375:32"/> may ſtill liue and eat the good things of the land.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Let vs proceed to a ſecond point.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine </seg>2</label> THere is no priuiledge, no not ſpirituall that can pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue a man fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a natural death, or the firſt deth: out of no court can a man fetch a writ of prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction againſt this Sergeant, no place will preſerue, no perſon can be priuiledged from it. Here the holy and good man, the righteous and religious man is taken from the earth and dieth: It is no maruel, though, as <hi>Iob</hi> ſpeaketh,<note n="r" place="margin">Iob. 14.1.2.</note> 
               <hi>Man that is borne of a woman, is of ſhort continuance, he ſhooteth forth as a flower, &amp; is cut down; he vaniſheth alſo as a ſhadow, and continueth not.</hi> But a man would thinke that<note n="ſ" place="margin">Iames <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.18.</note> 
               <hi>he that is begotten againe of Gods owne will by the word of truth: that</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">Iohn 3.5.</note> 
               <hi>hee that is borne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine of water and of the ſpirit</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:18375:32"/> and ſo<note n="u" place="margin">Iohn 1.13.</note> 
               <hi>borne not of blood, nor of the will of fleſh, nor of the will of man, but of God: yea</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">1. Pet. 1.23.</note> 
               <hi>borne a new, not of mortall ſeede, but of immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall, the word of God, which li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth and indureth for euer:</hi> A man (I ſay) would thinke that he ſhould not die: and yet behold the whole generation of Gods Children, they all die in their appointed time, and vndergoe death,<note n="y" place="margin">Non ſupplicium ſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>utum vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uendi. Seneca.</note> 
               <hi>not as a puniſhment, but as a tribute</hi> (as the heathen man ſpeakes) <hi>which euery man muſt pay for his life.</hi> Though the foole die, yet may not the wiſe man liue euer?<note n="z" place="margin">Eccleſ. 2.16.</note> 
               <hi>How dieth the wiſe man? as doth the foole:</hi> (ſaith the Preacher): but though the ſubiect die, yet cannot the Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne put away death with his Scepter.<note n="a" place="margin">Pſal. 82.6.</note> 
               <hi>I haue ſaid ye are Gods, and ye all are children of the moſt high: but ye ſhall die as a man, and ye Princes ſhall fall like others.</hi> But though Prince and people die, yet are not the Prophets ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed?
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:18375:33"/> 
               <note n="b" place="margin">Zach. 1.5.</note> 
               <hi>Your fathers, where are they, and doe the Prophets liue for euer?</hi> Examples of other times, experience of our owne teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vs, that all of all ſorts die, and are gathered to their fathers. <hi>Yea</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Etiam muta Clamant cadauera Baſil.</note> 
               <hi>the dumbe and dead bodies cry this aloud to vs.</hi> As <hi>Baſill</hi> of <hi>Seleucia</hi> ſaith of <hi>Noah:</hi> hee preached without preaching, euery ſtroke of the Arke was a reall ſermon of repentance, ſo euery corps wee follow and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company to the graue preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth really this truth to vs.</p>
            <p>And this truth hath certaine ground. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>1</label> Firſt, becauſe the Lord of life and death hath ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed it.<note n="d" place="margin">Heb. 9 27.</note> 
               <hi>It is appointed vnto men that they ſhall once die:</hi> The de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree was made <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.19.<note n="e" place="margin">Gen. 3.19.</note> 
               <hi>Thou art duſt, and to duſt thou ſhalt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne.</hi> If it be his decree, it muſt needes haue a certaine effect: the decree is certaine, the euent is ineuitable.<note n="f" place="margin">Pſal. 115.3.</note> 
               <hi>Our God is in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and he doth whatſoeuer hee
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:18375:33"/> will.</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Vol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſſe feciſſe eſt. Cypr. de Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plici martyr.</note> 
               <hi>Gods will is his deede</hi> (as <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſaith, if he haue once willd it, it is as good as wrought if he haue decreed it, it is as cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine as if it were done.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>2</label> Secondly, becauſe all of all ſorts and conditions are made of one mould and one matter,<note n="h" place="margin">Iob 4.19.</note> made of clay and earth, <hi>whoſe foundatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is in the duſt, which ſhall be deſtroied before the moth.</hi> Hence the Apoſtle calleth mens bodies<note n="i" place="margin">1. Corinth. 5.7.</note> 
               <hi>The earthly houſe of this Tabernacle.</hi> It is true that as there are difference of ſtars, though al made of th ſame mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: and difference of mettalls, ſome are gold, ſome ſiluer, ſome lead, ſome tinne, but all made of one earth: ſo are there diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of bodies, ſome more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent then other, and made of a purer earth, but yet all ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to corruption, as the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter whereof they are made is. It being the body then that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth and ſeeth corruption, one
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:18375:34"/> muſt die as well as another.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>3</label> Thirdly, becauſe all haue ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and all haue ſinne.<note n="k" place="margin">1 Iohn 1.8, 9, 10.</note> 
               <hi>If we ſay we haue no ſinne, we deceiue our ſelues, and make God a liar.</hi> The holy and beloued Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ranketh himſelfe with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and confeſſed, that he had ſtill ſin in him: <hi>He</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Qui ſe inculpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum dixerit, aut ſuperbus eſt, aut ſtultus. Cypr. de oper. &amp; Eleem.</note> 
               <hi>that ſaith he is without fault, is either proud or a foole, ſaith Cyprian.</hi> Then muſt all be ſubiect to death; for ſaith the Apoſtle<note n="m" place="margin">Rom. 5.12.</note> 
               <hi>As by one man ſinne entred into the world, and death by ſinne, and ſo death went ouer all, for as much as all men haue ſinned.</hi> Sinne the only cauſe, ſaith one, which en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged deaths dominion, and made all the world to become his tributaries, for had it not been for ſinne, death had neuer entred into the world.<note n="n" place="margin">Si Adam non peccaſſet, mortem non guſtaret. Aug: enchirid. cap. <hi>104.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>If Adam had not ſinned, he had not taſted death</hi> (as <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſpeakes) And the Lord ſaid<note n="o" place="margin">Geneſ. 2.17.</note> 
               <hi>In the day that thou eateſt thereof, thou ſhalt
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:18375:34"/> die the death:</hi> not actually, but potentially become mortall. Now that which is true in the root holdeth in the branches.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>4</label> Fourthly, becauſe ſinne which brought in death, might be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroied againe by death: this vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perous damme by ſuch a daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, this beaſt by ſuch a brood, had it not been for ſinne, death had neuer entred into the world and were it not for death ſinne would neuer goe out of the world: As <hi>Baſill</hi> ſaith,<note n="p" place="margin">Deiu mortem non fecit, ſed noſmet ipſi ex mente pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ua, nobis ipſis eti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am ſponte attraxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, quam Deus minimè prohibuit, ne immortalem in nobis morbum con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruaret. Baſil. ſerm. <hi>9.</hi> quod Deus non eſt author malorum.</note> 
               <hi>God made not death, but we our ſelues by our wicked minds, of our owne accorde, wee haue drawne it on our ſelues, which God did not at all forbid, leſt it ſhould keepe in vs an immortall diſeaſe.</hi> And as <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanius</hi> bringeth in <hi>Methodius</hi> diſputing with <hi>Proclus</hi> the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giniſt:<note n="q" place="margin">Inſtar medica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentariae purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis mortem Deus bene inuenit, quo ſic omnino in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culpabiles, &amp; in noxij inueniantur, &amp;c. Epiph. haer. <hi>64.</hi> &amp;c. methodio.</note> 
               <hi>God as the true Phyſitian hath appointed death to be a phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call purgation for the vtter rooting out and putting away of ſinne, that we may be made faultleſſe and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent:</hi>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:18375:35"/> and <hi>that as a goodly golden image,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>ſightly and ſeemly in all parts, if it be broken and defa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by any meanes, muſt be new caſt and framed againe, for the taking away of the blemiſhes and diſgraces of it, euen ſo man the Image of God being maimed and diſgraced by ſinne, for the putting away of thoſe diſgraces, and the repairing of his ruines and decaies, muſt by death be diſſolued into the earth, thence to be raiſed vp againe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, and without default.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> But what vſe may we make of all this? Firſt it is a care that euery one ought to haue to know they muſt die, and they cannot auoid it: the decree is gone out againſt them from the higheſt court of Parliament, and that from the moſt higheſt: what contempt were it not to take notice of it? eury one ought to labour to number his daies, and truely to know his mortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, the greateſt as well as the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:18375:35"/> meaneſt, the wiſeſt as the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleſt, for if any one then all and if any more then other, the greateſt, for they are not the leaſt, but rather the moſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to this, as they challenge themſelues to be of the fineſt of the common mould, ſo they muſt know that they are not by that exempted from the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon law of nature, and force of Gods decree, but as the finer the mettall, or the purer the matter of any glaſſe, or earthen veſſell, the more ſubiect it is to breaking, ſo they to mortality: And therefore both they, and all muſt labor for this ſpirituall Arithmeticke. <hi>To number their daies, which is a religious medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and ſound conſideration of their frailty and mortality.</hi> A thing worthy euery mans beſt diſpoſed thoughts and inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: for ſeenig euery man muſt die, and hath a courſe to finiſh, which being finiſhed, he muſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:18375:36"/> it is ſpeciall wiſdome to learne to know the length of his daies, as it were the length of his leaſe; for as hee hath vſed himſelfe in his farme, hee ſhall enter at the expiration of his time vpon a better or a worſe. <hi>Dauid</hi> for his learning a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, for his accepation a man after Gods owne heart, for his authority a King, was then ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſtudious in this knowledge, when after watching &amp; faſting hee beſought God to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed in it.<note n="r" place="margin">Pſal. 39.4.</note> 
               <hi>Lord let me know mine end, and the meaſure of my daies what it is, let mee know how long I haue to liue.</hi> So <hi>Moſes</hi> wiſe in all the wiſdome of <hi>Egypt</hi> and <hi>Iſrael,</hi> accounted faithfull in the houſe of God, prayed yet for this point of wiſdome to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed in it, as well himſelfe as others.<note n="ſ" place="margin">Pſalm. 90.12.</note> 
               <hi>Teach vs ſo to number our daies, that we may apply our hearts to wiſdome,</hi> like carefull Schollers who breake their
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:18375:36"/> ſleepe, and forſake their meate, and are often in meditations when they beate vppon ſome ſerious ſubuect.</p>
            <p>What thinke you it will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit a man, if by his skil it Arith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meticke hee be able to deale with euery number, and to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide the leaſt fractions, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to thinke of the numbering of his daies with the men of God, which are ſo few, &amp; euill?</p>
            <p>What will it profit him if by Geometry hee be able to take the longitude of the moſt ſpaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous proſpects, and not be able to meaſure that which the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet hath meaſured with his ſpan? What will it auaile him if with the Aſtronomer he be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to obſerue and know the motion of the heauens, and yet haue his heart ſo buried in the earth, that he cannot thinke of that which paſſeth away as ſwiftly as them? What profit if he be able with the Philoſopher
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:18375:37"/> to ſearch out the cauſes of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny effects, and to know the cauſes of many changes, as of the ebbing and flowing of the Seas, the increaſing, &amp; waning of the moone, and the like, and be not able to know his owne changes, &amp; the cauſes of them?</p>
            <p>Doubtles all this will profit him nothing, all his knowledge will be to little purpoſe in the end. Many men beate their heads about friuolous matters, ſome being more buſie to know where Hell is (ſaith <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi>) then how to auoide the paines of it, others pleaſing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in pelting and needleſſe queſtions to ſeeme ſingular a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt men, neglecting this, &amp; the like neceſſary things: but when they come to their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parting, they ſhall finde they haue ſpunne a faire thread, and wearied themſelues in vaine: euery one then, as <hi>Daniel</hi> ſearched and found out by the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:18375:37"/> bookes of <hi>Ieremiah</hi> not onely the returne, but the time of the returne of <hi>Iſrael</hi> to their own land, from their captiuitie; ſo by ſtudie of the Scriptures ought they to ſearch, &amp; ſo may they come to know the time of the returne from their exile on the earth, to their country in heauen; and though they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not find the particular day or yeare, yet they ſhall find it to be moſt certaine, and that which in ſhort time ſhall be finiſhed. And thus ſhall death when it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth be leſſe hurtfull, as a tempeſt before expected. Death is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to the <hi>Baſilisk</hi> which if ſhe ſee before ſhe be ſeene, there is ſome danger; but if a man firſt deſcrie the <hi>Baſiliske,</hi> the ſerpent dieth, &amp; then there is no feare: <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> So if death be not ſeene and prouided for before hand, there is great danger; but if it be ſeene and prouided for, the danger is paſt before their death come?</p>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:18375:38"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">eVſ </seg>2</label> Secondly, muſt euery one die? &amp; wil no priuiledg protect the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? nay, it is certaine that they can carry none of their priuiledges with them out of the world, as they brough them not into the world,<note n="m" place="margin">1. Tim. 6.7.</note> 1. Tim. 6.7. <hi>We brough nothing into the world, &amp; it is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine we can carry nothing out.</hi> It is wiſdom then in euery one, to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor to be fitted for this paſſage<note n="n" place="margin">Ad hunc exitum praeparem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r, mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis enim nobis opus eſt vitaticu: quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niam et multus eſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtus, multa ſic ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, multa ſolitudo. Non iam licet in diuerſorio requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſcere, non eſt quod <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>matur ab eo qui non hic omnia ſumpſerit, audi certe quid dicat virgines: Mat. <hi>25.</hi> ite potius ad ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentes, ſed profe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctae, non inuene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt. Chryſ. hom. <hi>51.</hi> ad pop. Aut.</note> 
               <hi>Let vs be prepared to this iourney</hi> (as <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſaith) <hi>for we haue need of much prouiſion, becauſe there is much heate, much drought, much ſolitude; no Inne, no reſting place, no place of abode: there is nought to be boght of him, who hath not taken all things here. Heare what the Virgins ſay.</hi> Mat. 25. <hi>Goe rather to them that ſel:</hi> but going, <hi>they found not.</hi> What ought we then to doe? wee muſt not ſo labour for the things of this life, from which me muſt be taken, and which wee muſt leaue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind vs; but for thoſe which
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:18375:38"/> concerne a better life, and wee may carry with vs: not for thoſe things which ſhall haue either <hi rend="sup">a</hi> 
               <hi>finem tuum,</hi> or <hi>finem ſuum;</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">Finem tuum, ant finem ſuum. Bern.</note> (as <hi>Bernard</hi> ſpeakes,) an end of thee, if thou haue not an end of them; either ſhall they be taken fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs, as they were from <hi>Iob;</hi> or elſe we from them, as the rich man was from his ſubſtance &amp; wealth: but for thoſe things which wee may carry with vs, and may either bring vs to, or adorne vs where wee muſt be perpetually, and for euer. It were a very fooliſh part, and a ſenceleſſe practiſe for ſtrangers when they are in exile, or far from their owne country, in a forraigne ſoile and dwelling, whence they are ſure to be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led either by their owne Prince, or caſt out by the Prince of the country, to lay out all they are worth vppon ſome farme or Lordſhip there, neuer proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding for that which they may
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:18375:39"/> carry with them to their county adorne them when they come there, ſpecially if the ſo imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of themſelues &amp; their eſtate, be a meanes to keepe them from the enioying of the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe of their country; yea a cauſe that they ſhalbe caſt in to priſon &amp; plunged into miſery: So it is but a madnes for vs to imploy all our care, and ſpend all our time and endeuour for this life, and things for it and the body, vpon earthly and tranſitory things, things wee found here, &amp; muſt leaue here.<note n="u" place="margin">2. Corinth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 5.6.</note> And being here from home, ſtrangers in the body, abſent from the Lord, and our owne land (as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh) whence we know wee ſhall be called, either by a naturall or a violent death, ordinary or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary, taken away by God, or thruſt out by the cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of men, neuer prouiding for that which muſt adorne vs
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:18375:39"/> there, or further our paſſage, yea procure our entrance: ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially when ſuch things, and the care for them, which was ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with the neglect of ſo great things, euen of ſo great ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſhall procure miſery and puniſhment, where the other would procure mercy and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe:<note n="x" place="margin">Hic iſta relin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quuntur, illa verò nobiſcum migrent, et iſtorum quidem rationem dabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, horum autem praemia repetimus. Chryſ. hom. <hi>63.</hi> ad pop. At.</note> 
               <hi>here theſe things are left behind vs, thoſe go with vs; of theſe we ſhall giue an account, of them we ſhall reape a reward</hi> (as <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſaith): wee muſt therefore imitate ſtrangers, who prouide for their departure, and ſtore themſelues with ſuch things that are both portable and profitable, as may ſtead them in their paſſage and poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of their country: ſo muſt we prouide for ſpirituall things, ſtore our ſelues with them, which we onely muſt car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry with vs, and cannot be taken from vs, &amp; ſhall be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modious to vs when wee come to our
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:18375:40"/> country. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſaith;<note n="y" place="margin">Virtute inutus talem habet ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtem quam non tantum tineae, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum &amp; mors ipſae ledere nequit, &amp; merito, non enim hae animae <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>irtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes ex terra ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginem trahunt ſed ſpiritus ſunt fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus. Chryſ. hom. <hi>47.</hi> ad pop. At.</note> 
               <hi>He which is indued with vertue hath ſuch a garment, which as moaths cannot ſo neither can death it ſelfe hurt, and not without cauſe; for theſe vertues of the mind, take not their beginning from the earth, but are fruites of the ſpirit.</hi> They will then be eternall riches, and wee ſhall be eternall by them; and though death diſſolue bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and ſoule, and deſtroy our preſent being in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> life, yet as <hi>Iuſtin Martyr</hi> ſpake for himſelfe &amp; others, to their perſecutors;<note n="z" place="margin">Vos occ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dere quidem poteſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, at nocere non pot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tis. Iuſt. Mart. Apol. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>You may kill vs, but yee cannot hurt vs.</hi> So death may kill vs, but it cannot hurt vs, while it comes thus expected and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided for, it may be to our great commoditie and advantage.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And now I will come to the third point.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine </seg>3</label> AN immature and vntimely death, for a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be taken
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:18375:40"/> away before he be come to the full period of his life, that in the courſe of nature, and the eie of reaſon he might attaine to, is a thing that may betide good men, and not be a curſe to them. Here <hi>the good man periſheth, is</hi> vntimely taken away. And this is the Iame that is in <hi>Eſay,</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Eſay 57.1.</note> 
               <hi>The righteous periſheth, the mercifull man is taken away, namely vntime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly:</hi> for if they died in a full age, it were not blame worthy for a man not to conſider it in his<note n="b" place="margin">1. Kings 14.13.</note> 
               <hi>He</hi> heart. So of <hi>Ieroboams</hi> ſonne <hi>only of Ieroboam houſe ſhall come to the graue, becauſe in him is found ſome goodneſſe, towards the Lord God of Iſraell in the houſe of Ieroboam,</hi> The Preacher teacheth vs this,<note n="c" place="margin">Eccleſ. 8.12.</note> 
               <hi>Though a ſinner doe euill an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred times, and God prolong his daies, yet I know it ſhall be well with him that feares the lord, and doe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence before him;</hi> that is, though God do not prolong their daies</p>
            <p>Now this truth is confirmed
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:18375:41"/> vnto vs by two arguments, the one drawne from the malice of the wicked againſt the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the other from the mercy of God to the godly.
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>1</label> For the firſt, the wicked through their malice ſeeke by all meanes to cut off the godly, becauſe their wickedneſſe and ſinfull life is reprooued by their godly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation, neither can they follow their ſinnes ſo freely as they would, nor ſo quietly without detection or checke. The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſaith, <hi>Caine</hi> ſlew and cut off <hi>Abel,</hi> and wherefore ſlew hee him? becauſe<note n="d" place="margin">1 Iohn 3.12.</note> 
               <hi>his owne works were euill, and his brothers good.</hi> As the Patriarches ſold <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> and ſent him out of the houſe of his father, becauſe he was a meanes they were<note n="e" place="margin">Geneſ. 27.2.</note> checked for their euil ſayings. This is that we haue in the booke of Wiſedome,<note n="f" place="margin">VViſd. 2.12.</note> 
               <hi>Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let vs defraud the righteous, for he is not for our profit, and he is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to our doings. He checketh vs
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:18375:41"/> for offending againſt the law, and blameth vs as tranſgreſſors of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline,</hi> verſ. 14. <hi>He is made to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooue our thoughts, it greeueth vs alſo to looke vpon him, for his life is not like other mens, his waies are of another faſhion,</hi> verſ 20. <hi>Let vs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne him vnto a ſhamefull death, for he ſhall be preſerued as himſelfe ſaith.</hi> But all this is not againſt them, but as <hi>Ioſeph</hi> ſaid of his brothers enuie,<note n="g" place="margin">Geneſ. 50.20.</note> 
               <hi>When you thought euill againſt me, God tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned it to good.</hi> So when they think and doe euill againſt them, God diſpoſeth it to good through his mercy, and that partly to their bodies, partly to their ſoules for their bodies:</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>2</label> Becauſe in the goodneſſe he affecteth them withall, he ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth them from the euill and the plagues to come. As <hi>Lot</hi> out of <hi>Sodome,</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Geneſ. 19.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>The Lord being mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull vnto him, the men brought him forth and ſet him without the Citie.</hi> So them out of the world,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:18375:42"/> and as <hi>Huldah</hi> the Propheteſſe ſent <hi>Ioſiah</hi> word by his meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and from the Lord,<note n="i" place="margin">2. Kings 22.20.</note> 
               <hi>Behold, I will gather thee to thy fathers, and thou ſhalt be put in the graue, in peace, and thine eies ſhall not ſee all the euil which I will bring vpon this place. Plotinus</hi> the Philoſopher as <hi>Auſtin</hi> hath it,<note n="k" place="margin">Hoc ipſum quod mortales ſunt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines corpore, ad miſericordiam dei partis pertinere arbitratus eſt, ne ſemper huius vitae miſeria teneantur. Aug. de Ciuit. l. <hi>9.</hi> cap. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>De ciuitate dei,</hi> ſaw this in part, <hi>This very thing that men are bodily mortall, hee thought it an appurtenance to the mercy of God the Father, leſt they ſhould alwaies be tied to the miſery of this life.</hi> It is no leſſe mercy to be taken ſooner away that they may ſee and ſuffer leſſe mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery which the length of their daies would effect.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>3</label> Now his mercy appeares to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards their ſoules, becauſe they are by this meanes freed, either from hauing their ſoules grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued with the ſinnes of other, or from grieuing God with their owne ſinnes, which are no ſmall benefits. For being led by the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:18375:42"/> ſame ſpirit that<note n="l" place="margin">2. Pet. 2.7.</note> 
               <hi>Lot</hi> was, they cannot chooſe but be vexed as he was with the vncleane con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation of the wicked. <hi>For</hi> it cannot be but as in the Prouerbs <hi>A wicked man is an abomination to the iuſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prouerbs 29.27.</note> 
               <hi>as he that is vpright in his waies is abomination to the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked.</hi> Againe they being indued with a true filiall feare, they grieue to offend ſo gratious a father, which they cannot but doe whiles they are here, but af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this life ſhall be freed from it. <hi>Auſtine</hi> reporteth that <hi>Cyprian</hi> vſed to comfort his friends in dying with this;<note n="m" place="margin">Non ſolum fidelibus non in vtilis eſt mor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> verum etiam vtitis reperitur quoniam peccandi periculis hominem ſubtrahit, &amp; in non peccandi ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritatem conſtituit. Aug. de praed. ſanct. lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>14.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Death is not not only not vnprofitable to the faithfull, but is alſo found to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable, becauſe it taketh a man out of the danger of ſinning &amp; puts him in ſecuritie of not ſinning.</hi> The ſooner they are freed from theſe, the greater bleſſing and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiection. </seg>
               </label>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> We find in the fift com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement long life promiſed
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:18375:43"/> as a bleſſing to an obedient and good ſonne, fearing God, and honoring his parents, to haue theſe daies ſhortned, is it not, ſeemeth it not to be a curſe?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Solution. </seg>
               </label>
               <hi>Sol.</hi> Whatſoeuer it ſeemeth, yet it is not. It is anſwered by ſome, that the bleſſing there pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, was a bleſſing peculiar and ſpeciall for the Iewes, for the Land of <hi>Canaan</hi> being the land of promiſe, and a ſpeciall pledge of Gods fauour to liue long, in it was a ſpeciall teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of Gods loue. For to be in it, though dead, was ſpecially reſpected of the Fathers, as we ſee by <hi>Iacob</hi> and <hi>Ioſeph.</hi> But theſe reſtraine this promiſe and Gods bounty too much. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is there any reaſon that it being annexed to a morall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept and written in the Law, ſhould not be generall and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall, yea the Apoſtle wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting vnto the Epheſians, doth ſo make it, where he ſeemeth, alſo
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:18375:43"/> to expound it.<note n="n" place="margin">Epheſ. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.3.</note> 
               <hi>That it may be well with thee, and that thou maiſt liue long on earth.</hi> Wherein he ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that it is not abſolutely a bleſſing, but ſo long as a man was well on earth; noting it elſe no bleſſing to liue, but rather a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour to bee taken away from the euill to come. Say the father promiſe his ſonne a large leaſe in ſome rich place, but very vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>healthfull, for his obedience and ſeruice; and after take him thence, and in a richer ſoile, and only healthfull aire, giue him a fee ſimple of ſuch a thing as for fruitfulneſſe and pleaſantneſſe far ſurpaſſing the other, hath he not delt faithfully and fatherly with him? <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> vſeth this ſimilitude, I confeſſe to a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent purpoſe, but yet it fitteth our point,<note n="o" place="margin">Si ad aliquem profectus mercato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem duobus propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitis lapidibus hoc quidem falſo, hoc autem pretioſo, &amp; diuitiarum multi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> trah. nec, illius par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ui pretiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deponens magnum accep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, nunquid illum incuſaſſes? nequa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quamſed potius ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſſes admiratus. Itidem &amp; nunc propoſitae ſunt duae vitae, temporalis &amp; aeterna, ipſas au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem venundat Deu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Sed hanc nobis non illam vendit, quid in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipientium inſtar pueroru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> triſtamur quod pretioſum acceperimus. Chryſ. hem. <hi>38.</hi> ad pop. Ant.</note> 
               <hi>If thou ſhouldſt come to a merchant, and of two ſtones laid be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore thee, the one falſe, the other right pretious, and very dearly pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſeable, and laying downe the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:18375:44"/> price of the leſſer, ſhouldeſt get the greater, wouldſt thou accuſe him? No verily, but wouldſt rather admire im? In like manner now there are two liues propoſed to vs, viz. a temporall, and an eternall: both theſe God ſets to ſale, but hee ſels vs the eternall, not the tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall. Why like ſilly children are we ſad, becauſe wee haue receiued the beſt?</hi> By theſe we may well perceiue that this is neither croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to Gods promiſe, nor a curſe to the godlies perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. I now come to the vſe of this point.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> Here is comfort ouer thoſe that are departed, when any man ſhall ſee his friend taken away by an vntimely death, nothing hath befallen him but that which hath done, may doe, and doth often betide good men, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected and beloued of God. In reſpect of the common iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of men, when the ſerge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant death areſteth a man (before he hath as it ſeemeth runne the
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:18375:44"/> hower glaſſe of his life, which nature might afford) they deeme it like the Prophet <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hijah</hi> that met with <hi>Ieroboams</hi> wife, and told her, that hee was ſent with heauy tidings, and namely with that ſpecially, viz.<note n="p" place="margin">1. King. 14.6.12.</note> 
               <hi>Thy child ſhall die.</hi> So theſe iudge it heauy tydings, to heare that their friends are like apples, pulled before they be ripe, but in this ſorrow here is ſweetnes, the beſt are ſubiect to it, and it is no extraordinary thing to them. Againe though as grapes, they be gathered before they be ripe, and as lambes ſlaine before they be growne, yet they haue this benefit before thoſe that grow longer, and liue more yeeres, they are freed from the violence of the wine preſſe, that others fall into, and eſcape many ſtormes that others liue to taſt of. To ſay nothing of the good they haue gained, of the glory they haue obtianed, though they
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:18375:45"/> haue loſt much, they haue gai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned more. As <hi>Tertullian</hi> comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the martyrs,<note n="q" place="margin">Si aliqua ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſti vitae gaudia, negotiatio eſt, ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid amittere vt maiora lucreris. Tertul lib ad Martyr.</note> 
               <hi>If thou haſt loſt any of the ioies of this life, it is tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to looſe ſome leſſer matter, that thou maiſt gaine greater.</hi> They haue made a moſt gainfull traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fique, and happy change, they haue loſt ſhadowes, and gained ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, they haue parted with lead and found gold, they haue loſt earthly things, and poſſeſſe heauenly, and are made very rich in a ſhort time, yea obtained that in a very ſhort time, which many labour for twice or thrice as long before they can obtaine it. None would grieue to ſee his friend come ſooner then ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary, more ſpeedily then vſually others doe to riches and honors, to ſee his friend or child outſtrip others, euen many thouſands, and obtaine wealth and dignity in their youth, which others ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine not till they be well ſtrick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en in age, and hoare headed; nay
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:18375:45"/> in ſtead of grieuing, they ioy much in it: Much more is here cauſe, when they haue obtained ſo ſpeedily ſuch a meaſure of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall riches, and ſuch height of heauenly glory in ſo ſhort a time.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> Here is inſtruction for euery good man, that when death ſhal come for him, as it may ſeeme vntimely, before the thred of his life be halfe ſpun out, hee muſt be informed to entertaine it kindly, as <hi>Lot</hi> did the Angels, who came to fetch him out of <hi>Sodom:</hi> for though he be pulled from his ſeate, which was to him as the plaine of <hi>Sodom</hi> ſeemed to <hi>Lot,</hi> as a pleaſant Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radice, yet ſhall he finde with <hi>Lot,</hi> he is taken away from the iudgements to come: howſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer he be taken away, either by the malice of the wicked or by the mercy of God, and that he is ſeperated from the ſinnes of the world, which grieued his
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:18375:46"/> ſoule, yea fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſinning himſelfe, &amp; his owne ſins, which grieued the Lorde, euen his ſo gratious &amp; kinde father. For while he is in this world, he cannot but ſinne hauing ſo much means to draw him to it; as <hi>Cyprian</hi> in his booke of mortality,<note n="r" place="margin">Quid aliud in mundo qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pugna aduerſus diabolum quotidie geritur, quam aduerſus ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cula &amp; tela con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictationibus aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duu dimicatur. Cum auaritia no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis, cum impudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citia, cum ir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, cum ambitione congreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſio eſt. Cum carna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libus vitus, cum illecebris ſeculari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus aſſi tua &amp; mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſta luctatio eſt, obſeſſa mens ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minis eſt vndi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que diaboli infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtatione vallata, vix occurrit ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis, vix reſiſtit Si auaritia proſtrata eſt, exurgit libido. Si libido compreſſa eſt, ſuccedit ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio: S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ambitio contempta eſt, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ra exaſperat, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſta ſuperbia, vin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia inuitat, inuid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a concordiam rum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit, amicitiam ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus abſcindit Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> maledicere, quod diuina lex prohibet. Compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leru iurare, quod non licet. Tot per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutiones animus quotidie patitur, tot periculis pectus vrgetur, &amp; dele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctat inter dioboli gladios diu ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> re? cum magis concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcendum ſit &amp; optandum ad Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtum ſubueniente velociter morte properare. Cypr. l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>b. de mortal. <hi>Reu. 22.17.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>What do we elſe in the world but fight a combat with Satan, then with daily conflicts in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter his darts &amp; weapons, wee muſt grapple with couetouſnes, wantonnes, with anger &amp; ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, we haue a daily and tedious combate with the corruptions of the fleſh, and inticements of the world. The mind of man is beſeiged and beſet on all ſides with anoian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces from Sathan, ſo that it is not able to reſiſt or withſtand euery one. If couetouſnes be ouercome of vs, ſome euill affection will aſſaile vs: if that euill affection be ſtrangled, vaine glory will afflict vs, if vaine glory be deſpiſed, wrath will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence vs; if wrath be pacified, then pride will puffe vs vp, drunkennes
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:18375:46"/> will prouoke vs, enuy will breake concord, heate will interrupt friendſhip. Thou ſhalt be forced to curſe, which the law of God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biddeth. Thou ſhalt be conſtrained to ſweare, which is not lawfull. The ſoule ſuffereth ſo many perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons daily, the heart is preſſed with ſo many dangers, and doth it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light ſtill to abide amongſt the ſwords of Sathan, and not rather deſire by the meanes of a ſpeedy death to haſten to Chriſt.</hi> When he ſhal then be pulled fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this euil &amp; brought to this good, to enioy ſooner the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God, &amp; the lamb, yea as a bride to his beloued Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groome, that that which the bride deſired <hi>that he would come,</hi> that ſhe might haue his preſence he inioies before his general co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, preuenting as it were his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming by his going to him by, the means of this imature doth.</p>
            <p>Now how ſhould that but be a welcome gueſt, how but a
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:18375:47"/> choice bleſſing, which as a gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle guide leadeth him to his Chriſt, carrieth his ſoule to hir beloued husband. This was the reſolutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of <hi>Ambroſe, who neither loathed life, nor feared to die, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, ſaith he, we haue a good Lord to goe to.</hi> This was the faith of <hi>Simeon</hi> who hauing Chriſt, praied to depart in peace. This was Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> gaine, when he ſaid, <hi>to die is to me aduantage:</hi> becauſe this paſſage was a diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, &amp; this diſſolution was to be from the body, &amp; this his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the body was to be with Chriſt, though it came vntime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Thus may and ought euery good man to reſolue with <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe,</hi> to pray with <hi>Simeon,</hi> to triumph with <hi>Paul,</hi> when hee ſhalbe carried ſwiftly from the Coaſt of his baniſhment to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his owne country, not with the wind onely againſt the tide, not with the tide againſt the winde, but both with winde &amp;
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:18375:47"/> tide to the hauen of happines, to the Heauen of bleſſednes, where hee ſhall enioy the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God, and the Lamb,<note place="margin">Pſalm. 16.11.</note> 
               <hi>in whoſe preſence is fulnes of ioy and at whoſe right hand there are plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures for euermore.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus much out of my Text fitting the preſent occaſion.</p>
            <p>ANd now (Honorable and beloued) I know you expect ſome diſcourſe of me, and from me, of the life and death of this truly honorable Lord. I profeſſe firſt to you, that I haue often grieued at the licentiouſnes of many of my brethren in this kind, whereby they haue beene very offenſiue, and made them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues euill thought of, and thoſe they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mended neuer the better, but haue giuen the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion that the hearers who knew the deceaſed better then them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, haue raked into their liues, and ripped vp their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:18375:48"/> carriage, to their great diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace, &amp; laid open that which happily would haue beene kept ſecret, if this occaſion had not drawne it out.</p>
            <p>But yet herein, me thinks I ſaw the ouer-ruling hand of the moſt wiſe God, ordering mens ſinnes and infirmities to make good his owne word;<note n="t" place="margin">Prou. 10.7.</note> 
               <hi>The name of the wicked ſhall rot.</hi> So that as <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſpeaketh,<note n="u" place="margin">Hoc ipſo quod contra volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m Dei fecerunt, de ipſis facta eſt volunta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> Aug En<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Laurent. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>166.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>In this that they did againſt the will of God, is his will fulfilled by them.</hi> But yet I haue euer iudged it moſt fitting to ſpeake ſomewhat liberally, ſo it might be done warantably, of publike perſons, and eminent men, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing well, <hi>Spe vel re,</hi> of the Church and common wealth, that they may be brought to ſee their loſſe, and they made ſenſible of the hand of God, in depriuing them of ſuch notable meanes of their good, and worthy inſtruments
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:18375:48"/> of their peace and proſperity, as of his kingdome and glory.</p>
            <p>Thus iudgeing, I will ſo practiſe in the preſent, by your patience, to ſpeake a few things of this deceaſed honourable perſon; the moſt hopefull Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman, of a ſubiect, for the common good of the Church and common wealth (if my loue deceiue me not) that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ages haue afforded vs, of what ranck &amp; condition ſoeuer they were: I ſay a few words of his life and death, by your pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, that when wee ſee his worth, we may conceiue of our owne loſſe, and be aſſured of his gaine; and ſo in ſorrowing for our ſelues, yet we may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioice ouer him. In ſpeaking of whom, I feare,<note n="u" place="margin">Ne tanti viri laudes oratione mea eleuare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> magis quam exornarem. Chryſ. de ſacerd. lib. Bern. ſerm. ſupra Cant. <hi>34.</hi>
               </note> as <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> did when hee fell occaſionally into the commendations of Saint <hi>Paul; Leſt my ſpeech ſhould rather blemiſh and diminiſh the
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:18375:49"/> praiſe of ſo great a perſonage, then any waies adorne it:</hi> I will doe what I can, and if I ſatisfie not mens expectations, as <hi>Bernard</hi> in another caſe, <hi>Culpetur ſane ingenium, non voluntas: Blame my wit, and not my will.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But why hold I you thus in ſuſpence? I will paſſe by the birth of this honorable perſon, and his progenitours, though it be worth the eſteeme to be borne of thoſe that are truely worthy and antiently noble, &amp; to deſcend from their loines. Yet it is more properlie an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>others, then his commendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and is common to thoſe who haue nothing commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in them, nor haue any pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit by it, no more then a chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel or riuer that ſloweth from a pure and wholeſome ſpring if it be corrupt &amp; defiled, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the world hath too many, who are not ſo much honoured by their noble aunceſters, as
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:18375:49"/> they diſhonour them and their ſtocke. <hi>Dignitas in indigno or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namentum in Luto,</hi> ſaith <hi>Saluian;</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">Saluian. ad ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. cathol. lib. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> Honor in an vnhonorable ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, is like an ornament in the dirt, a iewell in the dunghill more defiled then it can adorne. Alas for griefe, that in this age of the world it may be ſpoken to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, which <hi>Nazianzene</hi> reports was ſometime ſpoken to a No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble man diſpiſing another that was come of meane parentage, and boaſting of his owne nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie: <hi>Mihi inquit probro genus meum eſt, tu autem generi tuo.</hi>
               <note n="y" place="margin">Nazian. in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilem male morat.</note> 
               <hi>My parentage is a reproach to me, but thour art a reproach to thy paren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage.</hi> This honorable Lord as a thankfull man for honour re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, returned honour to his aunceſtors, and that with ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage, being no leſſe hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to them, then they were to him: I know they will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge and ſubſcribe to this with much ioy &amp; comfort.</p>
            <pb n="66" facs="tcp:18375:50"/>
            <p>I will omit to ſpeake of his education and bringing vp, which is the honour of his pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, hauing beene ſo religious and truly Chriſtian as it was. <hi>Non eſt parui apud deum meriti bene filios educare.</hi> So <hi>Hierome.</hi>
               <note n="z" place="margin">Hieron. epiſt. <hi>9.</hi> ad Sal.</note> 
               <hi>It is a thing of noe ſmale account with God, for men to bring vp their children well,</hi> and in the feare of God, eſpecially men Children, which as <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome</hi> ſaith, is<note n="a" place="margin">Magis intollera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilis &amp; cum ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iori formidine. Chryſ. de ſacerd. lib. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> A greater bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, and more full of feares and cares.</p>
            <p>I will not ſtand vppon his naturall parts of wit, memory, ſweetnes of nature, habilitie of body, all which were in him ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent, but they are common to many others, yet in this dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent, namely in the well vſing and applying of them <hi>A good wit</hi> (ſaith one) <hi>vnſanctified, is a prey for the Diuell;</hi> ſo I may ſay of the reſt: but when it is true of them which <hi>Bernard</hi>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:18375:50"/> ſaith.<note n="b" place="margin">Gratia ordinat quam donauit cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atio. Bern. tract. de gra. &amp; lib. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Grace doth order aright that which Creation hath giuen.</hi> Then are they honorable and comme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dable indeed. Such were they in this honorable perſon truly ſanctified, and religiouſly applied to all good, as ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare by that which follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</p>
            <p>For his learning, I muſt leaue it to others to ſpeake, that had occaſion to confer with him and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſe with him in that courſe, I meane for humane knowledge of tongues and arts, and the like, I know many both ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and Engliſhmen ſpeake ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirably of him. As ſome out of certaine knowledge teſtifie of him, that he had attained foure languages very ſufficiently, The <hi>Greeke, Latin, Italian, and French,</hi> being able to reade Greeke au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, and to make vſe of them in their owne language. Speak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Latine well and writing a pure and graue ſtile, ſo alſo
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:18375:51"/> he was able to confer with any ſtranger readily and laudably in the Italian &amp; French, as men of beſt iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t haue thought, able alſo to vnderſtand the Authors he read in the Spaniſh tongue. So for his knowledge in the Arts, ſpecially in Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phie, and the Mathematicks, ſome who are Maſters of theſe Arts, and others of note witnes with them, that his skill as well in the practike part as contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>platiue, was of that degree to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards perfection, as that he was not only to haue been ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted excellent, in reſpect he was a gentleman of noble ranke &amp; place; but that he might iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be paraleld with moſt of the beſt that were renowned in the only profeſſing of the ſame: For his knowledge in the Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rique of the art Military &amp; Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uigation, he had made ſo good a progreſſe therein, as ſome who vnderſtand thoſe arts well
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:18375:51"/> do witneſſe, he wanted nothing but the practiſe to a great per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection in them both. For his vnderſtanding in heauenly knowledge, and the myſteries of ſaluation, as his deſire was ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry feruent to it, ſo was his ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe very proſperous &amp; happy in it. For he had attained that meaſure, that I neuer knew in any of what ranke ſoeuer of his yeeres, (that did not intend to make it their profeſſion) I haue conferred with him many and many times, I neuer knew the queſtion come in our way, which he was not able ſuddenly and vnderſtandingly to ſpeake vnto.</p>
            <p>But to come to the beſt, and that which is moſt comfortable, as touching him, and may more make vs to bewaile our loſſe; This deſire of knowledge was not as <hi>Bernard</hi> notes of ſome, who deſired to know,<note n="c" place="margin">Eo fine tantum vt ſciant. Bern. ſerm. ſupra Cant. <hi>36.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>For that end only that they might know;</hi>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:18375:52"/> which is, <hi>Turpis curioſitas</hi> (ſaith the Father <hi>a filthy curioſity.</hi> Nor, as others who deſired it, <hi>vt ſcia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur ipſi; that they might be known,</hi> which is, <hi>turpis vanitas, foule va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity:</hi> Nor as others, <hi>vt ſcientiam ſuam vendant; that they may make ſale of their knowledge,</hi> which is <hi>turpis quaeſtus, filthy lucre:</hi> But it was as he ſpeaketh; others deſired knowledge, <hi>vt aedificent,</hi> that they might profit others, which was <hi>charitas,</hi> charity, and as others, <hi>vt aefidificentur, that they might be edified, &amp; prudentia eſt, and it is wiſedome.</hi> Of all theſe only, the two laſt are found free from the abuſe of knowledge, as who would therfore vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that they might do good.<note n="d" place="margin">Horum omnium ſoli vltimi duo non inueniuntur in abuſione ſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae quippe qui ad boc volunt intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gere vt benefaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant.</note> 
               <hi>Theſe two laſt are not the abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of knowledge, becauſe they deſire to know well, that they may doe well:</hi> ſuch I aſſure you was the deſire of knowledge in this honorable perſon, which I manifeſt thus vnto you.</p>
            <pb n="71" facs="tcp:18375:52"/>
            <p>The grace of ſaluation, that is, this ſauing knowledge by the Goſpell, teacheth not for the ſpeculation, but the practiſe of it, it being like the voice that bad <hi>Lazarus</hi> ariſe, and made him able to riſe out of his graue, and to walke and worke. I ſay, it teacheth three leſſons, &amp; ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles them that truly apprehend it, to worke three maine things. <hi>Sobriety, Iuſtice, Piety,</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Titus 8.11.12.</note> 
               <hi>The grace of God that bringeth ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vnto all men hath appeared, and teacheth vs that we ſhould liue ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berly, and righteouſly and godly in this preſent world.</hi> How well this noble worthy had both learned, and was enabled by the grace of ſaluation to practiſe theſe three, I will manifeſt to you in few words: of the firſt two more briefly; of the latter, more largely.</p>
            <p>For his ſobriety, he was a wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull, ſober, and chaſt man in his life; nay his lips not heard to
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:18375:53"/> vtter any vnchaſt, nay ſcarſely vnſeemly ſpeech, as many report of him, with whom happily he would haue ſpoken more libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally and opened himſelfe more freely then with me: which was the more commendable in him, becauſe he was as <hi>Hierome</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth <hi>in lubrica aetate, in a ſlippery age,</hi> in the flower of his youth; but yet more, becauſe: he liued <hi>in lubrico loco, in a ſlippery place,</hi> the Court; moſt of all, becauſe hee had bin a traueller in thoſe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces where are ſchooles of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſſe, whence few euer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne ſuch as they went out; but of good and chaſt, returne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſt, being vnchaſt when they went out, they are ſeuen fold more defiled then before. So was it not with him, but like fiſhes which retaine their freſh taſt, though they liue in ſalt wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; ſo in an vnchaſtage, in vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſt places, he euer kept his chaſtity, yea he grew in the loue
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:18375:53"/> of chaſtity, and hatred of all vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleannes.</p>
            <p>And no maruell, for he tooke the way to it; he auoided the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions, he ſpent not his time in courting of yong Ladies, and amouroſly beholding beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull women, the bellowes of luſt, and baites of vncleannes, of whom Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſpeaketh thus,<note n="f" place="margin">Videre illas ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt cordi, audire illas inflammat animam, tangere illas ſtimulat car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem; omne deni<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> quod cum faeminis agitur, laqueus eſt homini cum illis conuerſanti. Aug de cohab. cler. &amp; mulier.</note> 
               <hi>To ſee them, hurts the heart, to heare them, inflames the mind, to touch them ſtirres vp the fleſh, and laſt of all, all whatſoeuer is done with women (which are not their lawfull wiues) is a ſnare to that man that dealeth with them.</hi> But this chaſt ſpouſe eſteemed his books aboue their beauty, and in ſtead of daliance with them, his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light was in men of parts and learning, for arts and Arms. But beſides this, as a ſpeciall meanes of chaſtity, he was temperate in feeding, and rare in feaſting, and frequent in faſting (of which, when I come to his religion.) he
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:18375:54"/> was moreouer a great auoider of idleneſſe and ſleepe, the two nurſes of vncleannes; with his will he ordinarily neuer ſlept aboue ſix howres, and when he lay awake, he ſought to exclude all euill thoughts with medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſome heauenly things, as I ſhall tell you when I come to his piety.</p>
            <p>For his iuſtice, he had no publike place to ſhew him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in, he was but comming vp on the ſtage &amp; God called him away, and ſuffered him not to manifeſt what he had gotten by his carefull fitting himſelfe for ſuch a place: for his priuate carriage, I haue not heard, but that he dealt honorably and honeſtly with euery man that he had to doe with;<note place="margin">He attended vpon the Lady Electreſſe 10. yeers or there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abouts.</note> that great and honorable care he had that his fathers debts, which were very great by his manifold both priuate and publike occaſions, and ſome few of his own (which
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:18375:54"/> I am enformed to be no great matter) eſtabliſhing power in his honorable mother and exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutreſſe, to ſell all, or any part of the land, preſently and ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily to pay and diſcharge all: and when the gentleman who drew the conueiance demanded of him, if he aproued of that he appointed to be done, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed to this purpoſe; he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, <hi>Yes with all my heart, for my honor &amp; my honeſty are my nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt heires.</hi> If any thinke that to impeach his iuſtice, that he left not the land to the heire male, to vphold the houſe, I muſt tel the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that in iuſtice, the paying of iuſt debts ought to be preferred be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vpholding or houſes, and wil giue more co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort at the laſt: yea there can be no true com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort without care of this: and the taile being cut off as I am enformed (by his father) in this honorable reſpect, to pay euery man his owne, his ſiſters were
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:18375:55"/> neerer to him then his coſien german, both by the law of God and nature, who being honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Ladies, profeſſors of religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as it lieth in their power and the world lookes for it from them: ſo if they leaue no children to inherit, no doubt, they will haue an honorable care to vphold the houſe, and the name; which I think wilbe much to their honor</p>
            <p>And now honorable &amp; belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, I come to the third branch, &amp; the third effect of this ſauing knowledge, his godlineſſe and religion, of whom I may ſay as <hi>Saluian</hi> ſaith of one,<note n="g" place="margin">Erat fide nobilis quae omnibus ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per ornatibus or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namento eſt, quia ſine hac nihil tam ornatum eſt, quod ornare poteſt. Salu epiſt. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>That he was noble in that faith which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies in all addreſsings, is an orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, becauſe without this faith, there is nothing ſo ſpecious that can garniſh and beautifie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This, this is the Temple that ſanctifies the gold, this is the Altar that ſanctifies the offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, by this the ſobrietie and iuſtice (which in an heathen or
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:18375:55"/> ciuill man, without this, are but gliſtering ſinnes as,<note place="margin">Splendida peccata ſplendida virtutes.</note> 
               <hi>Auſtine</hi> cals them) in him were glorious ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues. For this in generall, ſuch was his pietie, that not I onely, but many others, better able to iudge then my ſelfe, will affirme with me, that we knew not any of what rank ſoeuer, in who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we diſcerned more, nay ſo feruent a deſire of ſauing knowledge, ſo conſtant a reſolution to practiſe al knowne good duties, ſo great tendernes of conſcience, and feare to offend God in the leaſt thing which hee knew to be ſin. How and whereby we diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned this, I will diſcouer to you in particular, which when you haue heard, I doubt not but you wil iudge, that we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceited not things amiſſe, but as they were.</p>
            <p>Wee diſcerned this, and it did diſcouer it ſelfe vnto vs two waies, by his priuate and publike exerciſes of pietie,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:18375:56"/> which were ſuch, as I ſay not, were rarely found in a young ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, more rarely in a noble man, moſt rarely in a young noble man; but ſuch they were, as are rarely found in ſuch meaſure in any man of what age and condition ſoeuer he be. I will firſt ſpeake of his priuate courſe, and tell you how he ſpent one day, and in like manner he ſpent all the daies of the yeare.</p>
            <p>His priuate exerciſe &amp; courſe of pietie was on this ſort; hee vſually roſe euery morning a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout 4. or 5. of the clocke, not willingly ſleeping aboue ſix howers, as ſoone as euer he was thorowly awake, hee in deuou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red religiouſly to ſet his heart in order, and to prepare it for goodnes all the day after, of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering the firſt fruites of the day and of his thoughts vnto God. Thus hauing tuned his beſt inſtrument, his heart, in the next place he read a Chapter
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:18375:56"/> of the holy Scripture; that done he went to praiers with his ſeruants in his chamber, after this he read ſome diuine treatiſe to increaſe his knowledge in ſpirituall things, and this for the greater part of an hower: he had of latter times read ouer in this courſe <hi>Caluins</hi> Inſtitutions, and was at the time of his ſicknes reading the workes of a reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend man now liuing, one M. <hi>Rogers.</hi> And all this hee did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that which was performed with all the familie, with whom hee ioined in the order his honorable father left in the familie namely, reading of the <hi>Pſalmes,</hi> and a chapter, togither with praier, according to the order of our Church, before dinner and ſupper, and ſinging of a Pſalme and praier after ſupper.</p>
            <p>But to returne to his mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning buſines, after hee had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed the former time in the
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:18375:57"/> manner aforeſaid, he with drew himſelfe to his cloſet, and after his owne priuat praier, diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed himſelfe to ſome ſerious ſtudie (if ſome ſpeciall buſines interrupted not his courſe) for the ſpace of 3. or 4. howers; after which time, he addreſſed himſelfe, if he had time before dinner, to diſpatch buſines, if any there were required of him, or to conuerſe and conferre with his friends, to better the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or be bettered by them, or to ride his great horſe, or walke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad. But why place I theſe with his religion? becauſe here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he kept himſelfe from idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and gaue no way to the temptations of Satan, knowing well that the flies ſettle vppon the ſweeteſt perfumes when they are colde, and corrupt them.</p>
            <p>Soone after dinner, if hee had the opportunitie, he ordinarily withdrew himſelfe for a while
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:18375:57"/> to the meditating vppon ſome Sermons which hee had lately heard, for which vſe, hee retained ſome 5. or 6. in his minde. Hee would not faile though he was diſappointed of that oppertunitie, to meditate vppon them before he ſlept, yea many times trauelling by land or water, hee performed this duety, and then would deſire his companions to forbeare talke, <hi>they might thinke a while</hi> he did ordinarily meditate and call to minde 4. or 5. in a day. The reſt of his afternoone hee gaue to buſines as the occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons were, and to ſtudie Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and to get inſtructions from them who were skilfull in the diſcipline of War, or in the Mathematikes and Nauigati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, wherein ſome report he had made great ſucceſſe for his age and time.</p>
            <p>After ſupper, hee betooke himſelfe to praier with his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:18375:58"/> &amp; that which is marke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able aboue many other things, after praiers with them, hee withdrew himſelfe from his ſeruants and friends, and there in a booke which hee kept for the account of his life, hee ſet down what he had done al that day, how he had either offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded or done good, and how he was tempted, and with ſtood them, and according to his ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, he humbled himſelfe; and ſuch was his wiſedome, that ſuch temptations as were not fit (as I ſuppoſe) to come to any mans view but his owne, and his Gods, he writ in a pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar Caracter knowne to none. After this, giuing himſelfe to his reſt, as riſing he had care to ſhut out euill by poſſeſſing his heart with good thoughts, and the reading of the holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; ſo had he care to ſhut vp his heart againſt ſuch things: one of his Chamber, as he was laying
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:18375:58"/> him to reſt,<note n="*" place="margin">I haue knowne a great light of our Church (who now reſts in peace) vſe the ſame practiſe.</note> reading a Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter or two of the ſacred word of God. And this was not taken vp for a fit, and as a noueltie, but hee continued it for the ſpace of 4. yeares laſt paſt, as ſome informe me, that is, from <hi>Ianuary</hi> 1609. to the 15. of <hi>February</hi> 1613. the day when he tooke his bed, ſome 12. daies before his death.</p>
            <p>And now honourable and beloued, for his publike exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes, which you may wel thinke were carefully and conſcionably performed. For he that had ſuch care to approue himſelfe to God in priuate, had no leſſe care to approue himſelfe both to God and man in publike. This appeareth in his religious vſe of the time and meanes of Gods worſhip, and his owne edification and ſaluation.</p>
            <p>He was a moſt religious obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer of the Saboth, in publike &amp; priuate duties, profeſſing to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:18375:59"/> the publike meanes (if hee were where hee could enioy them) before all priuate, though they were differently perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and had reſolued, though hee entertained an houſhold Chaplaine, yet euer to frequent the publike aſſemblies vppon the Sabboth day, a thing wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy the noting, to the reproofe of many of his owne, as of infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior ranke, who ſo much neglect the publike aſſemblies. And for his preſent practiſe, he did not miſſe ordinarily twice a day to heare the word publikely: no not when he was a Courtier: yea he hath ridden 4. miles to the publike worſhip of God, when he could not enioy it nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer. After he had heard, he vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally withdew himſelfe from company before dinner, if hee were ſo fitted for circumſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, that he might for the ſpace of halfe an hower meditate vpon what he had heard, or for ſome
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:18375:59"/> other priuate meditations. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the afternoones publike ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe (two of his ſeruants ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing written, his memory being ſuch as it exceeded often times all their writings) he repeated with his ſeruants before ſupper both the Sermons, and writ them down in his night-booke, &amp; after all this, he prayed with them, wherein he had a great gift. And that which helped him the better to keep the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both, hee was conſtantly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed vppon Saturday at night, beſides his account for the day, to call himſelfe to a ſtrict account how he had ſpent the whole weeke, that accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as he found his eſtate, hee might better fit himſelfe to ſanctifie the Sabboth following. In the morning he repeated to his ſeruants as hee was making ready, thoſe ſeruants which hee had heard the Sabboth before. Note this, not out of time,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:18375:60"/> though ſomewhat out of place, that a moſt inward familiar of his hath, fin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the deliuery of this acquainted me with: that vpon the Saturday he tooke a view of all the weeke, ſo vpon the moneth Saturday, hee tooke a view of al the former moneth, to ſe how he had bettered, as one weeke more then another, ſo on moneth more then another, how he had added &amp; got more grace and ſtrength of pietie.</p>
            <p>In the hearing of the word, he was one of the moſt atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue, and reuerend hearers that euer I obſerued, or mine eies haue ſeene, that haue ſeene ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thouſands; for he well knew that he was before God, and that he heard not the words of man, but God: and aſwell did he acknowledge, that it is but the errour of great men to thinke they haue a priuiledge to be leſſe reuerent and regard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in hearing, then the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:18375:60"/> in the congregation: yea he knew that Kings Scepters are as much inferiour to Chriſts Scepter, as he that beares it is inferiour to Kings: therefore when he came to heare, he wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly laid downe his honour at Chriſt his feete.</p>
            <p>For the Sacrament, he receiued it conſtantly (if by any conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence he could) euery firſt Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day of the month, &amp; to fit him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to feaſt at Chriſts table, he faſted the Saturday before (beſides many other times when hee humbled himſelfe) ſpending the day in praier, with meditation, and examination of himſelfe and his eſtate, how it was with him ſince his laſt receiuing, neuer comming out of his ſtudie (vnleſſe very im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunate occaſions preſſed him) till towards ſupper time, nor medling with any buſines that day. On the Sunday mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, beſides his ordinary pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:18375:61"/> he read the 1. to the <hi>Corinth.</hi> 11. where the inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Supper is ſet downe. And for the ſpace of an hower, hee read with his ſeruants that ſhould communicate with him, a little treatiſe that is in print, teaching men how to bee pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for worthy receiuing. Thus carefull was this worthy to be fitly prepared for his Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiours ſupper, that he might be a worthy receiuer.<note n="*" place="margin">Note, that he was ſo free from oſtentation in all theſe, that he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted no man either to pray with him, or to repeat the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons with him but his ſeruants, &amp; his one friend he ſo deerly eſtee<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>med, (S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Ed. Har.</hi>) neither did he admit him, but after a great time of acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and him only did he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint with theſe priuat and ſecret holy duties, ſaue but when for his better informing, he had confere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce with ſome lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Miniſters.</note> And all this pietie and godlines did this noble heart practiſe in this age (to ſpeake no more particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly you may if you pleaſe, apply it to other particulars) in this age, I ſay, which is ſuch as <hi>Saluian</hi> complained his times were, that is, wherein,<note n="h" place="margin">Si quis ex Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libus conuerti ad Deum caeperis, fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tim honorem No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitatis amittit. O quantus in Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtiano populo honor Chriſti eſt obi reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gio ignobilem facit. Sal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. lib. <hi>4.</hi> de Gub. Dei.</note> 
               <hi>If any of the Nobles began to be conuerted vnto God, ſtraight way hee loſt the honour of his Nobilitie: O how great is the honour of Chriſt among Chriſtians, where religion makes men ignoble!</hi> This is for
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:18375:61"/> Atheiſts or Papiſts, it is enough and too much for them, to ſcorne men for religion: how impious a thing is it for Chriſtians to contemne men for the religion of Chriſt? As <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome</hi> to ſome,<note n="i" place="margin">Qui chriſtianum te dicis Gentilium arma depone, aut ſi tu numero ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiumes, oſtende te libere aduerſariu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vt Ethnicorum ſuſcipias vulnera. <hi>Hierome</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Thou which calleſt thy ſelfe a Chriſtian, lay downe the weapons of the Gentiles, or if thou art of the number of the enemies, freely profeſſe thy ſelfe an aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, that thou maieſt feel the ſmart of infidels.</hi> So I to theſe, if you profeſſe your ſelues Chriſtians: Oh that you would turne Atheiſts, or Papiſts, or elſe lay aſide the bitter arrowes of Atheiſts and Papiſts, if you bee of the number of ſuch, profeſſe your ſelues no longer Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, but ſuch, that you may be eſteemed for ſuch, and either be auoided, or rewarded as ſuch. Pardon (I pray you) my di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion. In this age, I ſay, thus affected, wherein as <hi>Saluian</hi> ſpeaketh in the place before,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:18375:62"/> 
               <note n="k" place="margin">Per hoc omnes quodammodo mali eſſe coguntur ne vites habeantur. Salu. ib. vt ſupra.</note> 
               <hi>By this meanes, all in a manner are compelled to be euill, leſt they ſhould be accounted vile.</hi> Euen in this age was this Honorable worthy, that I may ſpeake in the phraſe of the Apoſtle with ſome change,<note n="l" place="margin">Philip. 2.15.16.</note> Blameles &amp; pure, and the ſonne of God, without rebuke, in a naughty and crooked nation, amongſt whom hee ſhined as a light in the world, holding forth the words of life, and did reioice in the day of Chriſt, that hee had not run in vaine, neither had laboured in vain: yea &amp; reſolued with the Kingly Prophet <hi>Dauid,</hi> that if this were to be vile, when it was for the Lord &amp; for his ſeruice, he would yet be more vile then thus, knowing well the time ſhould come, that he ſhould be had in honour of thoſe that diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honoured him, and that for theſe things.</p>
            <p>Now all this pietie was inſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perably attended vppon with
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:18375:62"/> two inſeparable fruites of true godlines, the manifeſt proofe of the truth of it: Loue to all reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious perſons, and ſpecially to faithfull and painefull Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters; and abundance of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion towards the needy ſaints and members of Chriſt, of which many particulars might be giuen, but one may ſerue for many.</p>
            <p>I am certainely and credibly informed, that ſince his returne fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his trauels, by way of thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes to God, and for refre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing of the poore members of Chriſt, he gaue yearely, by the hands of a priuate friend (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides many and many occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onall workes of charitie) the ſumme of twenty pounds, and in the firſt Sabboth ſaue one, he was in the land, after his returne (hauing ſpent the Saturday be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it with his Turor, in faſting, praier, &amp; thankſgiuing) he ſpent in publike hearing the word, &amp;
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:18375:63"/> receiuing the Sacrament, giuing to the poore of that place, into their baſon, fiue pounds, and gaue other forty pounds to be beſtowed vppon poore Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and other Chriſtians, for the reliefe of their preſent ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie: yea ſuch was his libera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity in this kinde, (which is come to my knowledge by his accounts) that he gaue the tenth of his allowance to the poore, and other good vſes; his allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance being a thouſand pounds the yeare: beſides what hee gaue in the way as hee walked and trauelled, and in the ſtreetes, which he did often, and much, but what it was, no man can tel. Finally, all theſe were beautifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and adorned with ſuch ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable humility, as is rarely found in any, ſpecially in thoſe, that haue things, which na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally for the moſt part puffe vp the minde, as nobility, and many naturall indowments.
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:18375:63"/> Nay, not in thoſe, who haue many ſpirituall prerogatiues, many gifts and graces, that haue learned Chriſt, yet haue they not ſo learned of Chriſt, as this Honourable worthy had done, to be<note n="m" place="margin">Matth. 11.28.</note> 
               <hi>Meeke and lowly in heart.</hi> Of which I will vſe, and to whome I will apply onely that of <hi>Bernard,</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">Decor animae hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militas eſt, verum in eo qui grauiter peccauit, &amp; ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manda non tamen admiranda humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litas. At ſi quis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocentiam retinet &amp; nihilominus humilitatem iungit nonne is tibi vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur geminum ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mae poſſidere deco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem? Bern. ſupra Cant. ſerm. <hi>45.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>The beauties of the minde is humility, but in him who hath griuouſly tranſgreſt, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer humility may be to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced, yet not at all admired. But if a man keepe his innocencie, and withall addes himilitie, ſeemes not this man vnto thee to poſſes a double beauty of his ſoule?</hi> This Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable veſſell was double gilt, with true and intire innocencie (though imperfect through humane frailty) and true hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility. Thus was hee decked, and thus were all his graces and gifts adorned, all ſeeming and truely appearing ſuch as they were, becauſe hee was by
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:18375:64"/> this ſo nigh to men, and not by loftines, and pride lifted vp a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue, and remoued from men.</p>
            <p>Thus haue I diſcourſed to you of his life, and am come to the 15. of February, laſt paſt, when hee was viſited with ſicknes from God, whereof he died.</p>
            <p>Touching his carriage and comforts therein, wee cannot doubt but that it was very religious, and theſe very great, when ſuch a life went before, wherein there was ſuch prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration and prouiſion, ſuch a foundation laid vp in ſtore, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this euill day. I am onely accquainted with them by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, for I was neuer with him, though I much deſired it and often, yet the wiſdome of thoſe that were about him, thought it not fit, fearing not his death, till it was very late, &amp; he without hope of recouery, and I diuers miles remote from him.</p>
            <pb n="95" facs="tcp:18375:64"/>
            <p>That which was deliuered vnto me, by one that was with him all the time, or moſt of his ſicknes, whom I dare truſt, not mine owne eares better (other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe I am iealous of all friends reports in this caſe) I will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer vnto you as briefely as it was deliuered vnto me, which was thus. From the firſt day of his ſicknes, hee apprehended ſtrongly the expectation of death (though diuers thought nothing leſſe till a day or two before his dying day) &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hee addreſſed himſelfe thereunto; and beſides his me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations, hee called often for others to pray, and often vſed praiers himſelfe, confeſſing, and that often, both his ſinnes, and his faith and vndoubted hope of ſaluation by Chriſt; and with great alacritie he profeſſed that he feared not death, in what ſhape ſoeuer he came. He brake forth often into heauenly
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:18375:65"/> ſpeeches expreſſing his deſire to be diſſolued, and to be at home with his God and Father, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing not two howers before his death, that he ſtill felt the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured comforts of his ſaluation by Chriſt, &amp; ſo finiſhed his life in peace and ioy of the holie Ghoſt, vttering neere his death theſe longing words, <hi>O that ioy, O my God when ſhall I be with thee?</hi> Which ioy he vndoubted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enioyeth, and is with his God in glory and euerlaſting happineſſe.</p>
            <p>Thus honorable, and belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, you ſee by theſe things, the worth and excellency of this deceaſed perſon, honorable both by nature and grace, the more his worth was by theſe naturall and ſpirituall endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, the greater our loſſe, and the greater his gaine, and the more cauſe haue we to ſorrow for our ſelues, though to reioice on his behalfe. The whole
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:18375:65"/> hath cauſe to mourne, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waile, and many particulars to bewaile a part.</p>
            <p>His honorable mother, whom God hath depriued of hir ſonne, hir only ſonne, of ſuch a ſonne; ſuch a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtaffe and ſtay of her age, and ſuch a ioy of her life.</p>
            <p>His honourable ſiſters, from who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Lord hath taken ſuch a noble &amp; worthy brother, who would haue been not only a crowne of their honor, but a furtherer of them in the way of piety, and godlineſſe, to the crowne of glory.</p>
            <p>His kindred and aliance, who are depriued of ſuch an honor of their houſe, and ſuch a glory of their name.</p>
            <p>His kinde and familiar friends, who are bereft of ſuch a true harted <hi>Ionathan,</hi> one that was very kind vnto them, <hi>whoſe loue vnto them was wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful,</hi> ſpecially to him who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in his Wil, <hi>his deare friend.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>.</hi> Ed. Harwood.</note>
            </p>
            <pb n="98" facs="tcp:18375:66"/>
            <p>His ſeruants, that haue ſuch a maſter taken fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their heads, the ground of al their future hopes.</p>
            <p>And not theſe only, but more generally others haue cauſe to mourne and bewaile, as the Church, who hath loſt ſo hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and noble a <hi>Theophilus,</hi> that would haue defended her truth and doctrine; ſuch an honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Obadiah</hi> that would haue hid and protected her Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters.</p>
            <p>The common wealth, and ſpecially this little Shire where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of he was L. Lieutenant, that hath loſt ſo hopefull a <hi>Nehemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah,</hi> who would haue ſet him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe for the publike good, and giuen example and encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to keepe the Sabboth, and haue charged them ſo far as his power had extended, to haue carefully obſerued it, and ſo go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerned them that he would not only not oppreſſe them him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, but haue to his vtmoſt po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:18375:66"/> prouided that they ſhould be free from the oppreſſion of others. And here I will not omit that which may make the loſſe the greater, ſomething ſince brought vnto me by his deare friend, of two purpoſes he had for experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, to adde to the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer grounds of his ſtudy, the better to haue enabled himſelfe for his Countries ſeruice. The one by a voyage to ſea into ſome places, the knowledge where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of for war by ſea would haue been moſt vſefull; another by land, into one of our neighbour countries, fitteſt to haue enrich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his mind in the knowledge of land-ſeruice. Thus is there both generall and ſpeciall cauſe of mourning and lamentation; in reſpect of our ſelues: but ſee what great cauſe we haue of reioycing for him.</p>
            <p>What cauſe of reioycing and thankfulneſſe hath his honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble mother, though ſhe hath
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:18375:67"/> loſt her heire, yet to ſpeake in <hi>Chryſoſtomes</hi> words vnto her,<note n="o" place="margin">At haeredem bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſucceſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem non habes: &amp; quid malebas eum tuorum an caeleſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um haeredem fieri? Quid vero cupis eum pere<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ntiae ſuſcipere, quae paulo poſt eſſet di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſurus, an per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manentia &amp; im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mubilia? non hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redem eum ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſti, ſed ipſum prote Deus habuit. Chryſ. hom. <hi>69</hi> ad pop Ant.</note> 
               <hi>But you haue no heire, nor any ſucceſſor of your goods: well, and had you rather he ſhould be inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritor of theſe of yours, then of thoſe heauenly? What doe you deſire he ſhould enioy periſhing things, which within a ſmall while he muſt caſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, or permanent and immoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able? Nay, you had not an heire of him, but God had him for you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His honorable ſiſters in their ſorrow may reioice ouer him, for though as <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſaith,<note n="p" place="margin">Propriorum non fuit fratrum co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haeres, ſed Chr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſti conſtitutus eſt Chryſoſt. quo ant.</note> 
               <hi>He was not coheire with his pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate brethren, yet he is made co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heire with Chriſt.</hi> And that not in hope, but in preſent poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; he now at his full age, they but in their nonage as yet.</p>
            <p>How may his worthy friends roioyce for him, when we can ſay to them as <hi>Hierome</hi> to <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liodorus,</hi> comforting him ouer the death of his Nephew <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potian,</hi> who died in his youth,
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:18375:67"/> 
               <note n="q" place="margin">Intelligeres illum non emori ſed emig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>are, &amp; mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> amicos non relinquere. Hier. epiſt. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Thou ſhouldſt vnderſtand that he doeth not die but deceaſe, And only change his friends, not leaue them.</hi> So they ſhould be informed, that he is not dead, but tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated, &amp; hath not left his friends but changed them, for far more honorable and glorious then they, and ſo to reioyce in reſpect of him, leſt they may ſeeme to enuie his happineſſe.</p>
            <p>What cauſe of reioiycing hath the Church for him, ſo deare a child of hirs, that hath left the militant, but is poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of the triumphant Church, that hath left the ſtate of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litancie and warfaring, and is in the ſtate of triumphancy and victory.</p>
            <p>How may the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth and this Shire reioyce ouer him, that is taken from an earthly gouernment, to an hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly regiment; from ruling with men, to raigne with Chriſt, and hath left theſe
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:18375:68"/> few corruptible enſignes of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, but now poſſeſſeth true honour, and an immortall crowne.</p>
            <p>Finally, how may we all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce for him, and change our note as much as may be, forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting our owne loſſes, and think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his gaine. As <hi>Bernard</hi> of his friend <hi>Gerard,</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">Et meum faleor luctum poene in cantum conuertit dum intentus gloria ecius, propriae ferè miſoria obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſcor. Ber. ſuper Cant. <hi>26.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>And I confeſſe it turnes my mourning almoſt altogether into ſinging, wholes being intent vpon his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, I forget almoſt my owne mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now honorable and beloued, to draw towards an end, If for all this, his loſſe and the want of his preſence bee drieuous to you, and that ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in generall or particular you deſire his preſence, and to ſee him; let me ſpeake to you as <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> to ſome that were like affected,<note n="ſ" place="margin">Ipſum cernere de ſidera<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>? eandem cum eo vitam viue &amp; ſacram ocius illam acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pis praeſentiam. Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yſ. hom. <hi>69.</hi> ad pop. Ant.</note> 
               <hi>Doe you deſire to ſee him? then liue a life like vnto him; and ſo you ſhall the ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:18375:68"/> receiue that his ſacred pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence.</hi> So I to you, lead the ſame life with him, and you ſhall ſoon enioy his holy and comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble preſence: but if you will not, neuer looke to enioy him and it again. If this were the way that he trauelled Eaſtward to the heauenly Hieruſalem, if you goe Weſtward towards the curſed citie <hi>Hiericho,</hi> you ſhall neuer come to <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> the place of bleſſedneſſe and happineſſe.</p>
            <p>For if this be the way where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he hath paſſed, in the end whereof he hath attained to bliſſe and happineſſe; and if this be the only way, when there is but one way, whoſoeuer wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth in another way, cannot come to this eſtate.</p>
            <p>If he in the way of true cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtity, vpright iuſtice, holy piety, hath now the fruition of hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe, and enioyeth the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God himſelfe, and his
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:18375:69"/> Sonne, and his owne bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, Lord and husband. Who ſoeuer imitates not him in theſe, (I ſay not) whoſoeuer attaineth not to the imperfect perfection of theſe things that he had done, but whoſoeuer doth not care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ſtriue to it, but liues in vnchaſtity and vncleanneſſe, in iniuſtice and vnholineſſe, either ſcoffing, contemning, and neglecting this way, and courſe, ſhall enioy hell in ſtead of heauen, &amp; torments in ſtead of bleſſedneſſe; the iuſt wages of God for ſuch workers of iniquity.</p>
            <p>But to conclude all, It is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten of <hi>Hierome,</hi> that when hee had read the life and death of <hi>Hilarion,</hi> and ſaw that after hee liued religiouſly, he died moſt comfortably, and happily, ſaid, <hi>Well, Hilarion ſhall be the cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion that I will imitate.</hi> So now that you haue heard the life and death of this Right wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:18375:69"/> Noble, and are truelie informed how truelie religious the one, and certainly comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table the other was, ſay you with <hi>Hierome,</hi> well, <hi>This noble ſhall be our champion, whom wee will imitate, we wil follow his Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitie, his Iuſtice, his Piety will we imitate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo if you indeuour and doe, ſay and performe, you ſhal be ſure to enioy that in fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture time, which he poſſeſſeth in the preſent, heauenly and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall bliſſe and happineſſe, through the merits and mercies of Ieſus Chriſt, to whom with the Father and the Holie ghoſt, be aſcribed of vs and in all the Churches of the Saints, <hi>All glory, and maieſty, and dominion, and power, now and for euer, Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:18375:70"/>
            <head>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> obitum inopinum, &amp; praematurum Clariſſimi Baronis, D. <hi>Ioannis Haringtoni,</hi> Altae Indolis, <hi>&amp; Maximae Spei Adoleſcentis, Epicedium.</hi>
            </head>
            <l>IMmodicè ſi quis migrantem ad Sydera flebit,</l>
            <l>(Praeſertim vt nunc ſunt Tempora) flendus erit,</l>
            <l>Vt mare, perpetuis iactatur vita procellis,</l>
            <l>Mors placidus Portus, perfugium, Requies.</l>
            <l>Aurea, quae Priſci celebrarunt, Secula, Nugae,</l>
            <l>Ferrea quae fuerant Tempora, ſemper erunt.</l>
            <l>Qui antiquo vixit, Pater olim Hebraeus, in Aeno,</l>
            <l>Conqueritur paucos difficileſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> Dies</l>
            <l>Militiae humanae: quantô magis, heu magis iſto</l>
            <l>Si in ſenio Mundi degeret ille Senex?</l>
            <l>Quo pietas vitio eſt virtus, Probitaſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> fideſque,</l>
            <l>Ludibrio: cunctis Nil niſi turpe placet.</l>
            <l>Clare Heros, Nos te foelicein agnoſcimus, iſtis</l>
            <l>Sordibus ereptum, Coelicoliſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> datum.</l>
            <l>Delicia Iuuenum flos verae Nobilitatis,</l>
            <l>Vnica ſpes magnae, praeſidiumque Domus</l>
            <l>Ecce caedit ſubito: (triſte omen) ſcilicet Illo</l>
            <l>Indignifuimus dignior ille Polo.</l>
            <l>Nos Res lugemus noſtras, Eccleſia luget,</l>
            <l>Interitum deflet Patria meſta tuum.</l>
            <l>Vtra<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> damna dolet propria &amp; diſpendia, Lumen</l>
            <l>Hec deflet, columen Altera meſta gemit.</l>
            <l>Te Nobis vitia, et Mores rapuere maligni,</l>
            <l>In Coelis Virtus Te tua ſancta locat.</l>
            <l>Terra tegit Corpus, Mens aurea regnat Olympo,</l>
            <l>Fama Anglos inter celſa perennis erit.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>Poſuit <hi>Fran. Hering.</hi> D. M. moerens damnum, publicum, priuatum.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:18375:70"/>
            <head>
               <hi>An elegy vpon the vntimely deceaſe of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> honorable and vertuous Lord HARINGTON.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>LIght ſorrowes talk, great grief<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> are tongueleſſe quite,</l>
               <l>Amaz'd, aft<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>niſht, Apoplecticall;</l>
               <l>Why do I then, (vaine man) ſeek to recite</l>
               <l>That ſad euent which lately did befall</l>
               <l>That worthy houſe of late by iuſt demerit</l>
               <l>Aduanc'd to honor great, and greater credit?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>That noble houſe which I do thus deſigne</l>
               <l>VVell knowne to all and better much beloued</l>
               <l>In vertue, fau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ur, glory, ſo did ſhine,</l>
               <l>That few in England were ſo vvell a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>proued</l>
               <l>In Court, in City, country, thou mighiſt heare,</l>
               <l>No ill, all good of <hi>Harington</hi> echwhere.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>To him our King his ſecond Iewell deare,</l>
               <l>The Princeſſe his ſole daughter did commit,</l>
               <l>VVho's linckt in mariage to that German Peere</l>
               <l>VVhoſe vvorth the world admires; A match ſo fit.</l>
               <l>So happy, that who thinks vpon that day,</l>
               <l>Lifts vp his hand and thanks to heauen doth pay.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Ten yeeres the father of this matchleſſe ſonne</l>
               <l>Had in that honorable ſeruice ſpent,</l>
               <l>VVhen the laſt act of loue was to be done,</l>
               <l>To bring Her home, and giue Her full cont<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt;</l>
               <l>Content to Her, to Him that did attend</l>
               <l>Fatall it prou'd, with ſeruice life doth end.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>At his returne for England, nature ſoile,</l>
               <l>A ſickneſſe fierce, death<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Lictor doth arreſt,</l>
               <l>This worthy Lord, and cruelly diſpoile</l>
               <l>Of ſtrength of ſleepe; At laſt from noble breſt</l>
               <l>It draue <hi>Prometheus</hi> ſparke, and cauld it flie</l>
               <l>From whence it came vnto the ſtarry skie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>VVhat <hi>Homers</hi> pen can wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>thily expreſſe,</l>
               <l>Of that great Lady (thus in forrein parts</l>
               <l>Bereft of her deare Lord, all comfortleſſe;)</l>
               <l>The deepe diſtreſſe? The ſad and mournful hearts</l>
               <l>Of her attendants none can well relate,</l>
               <l>B the that was in that or the like ſtate.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:18375:71"/>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the firſt act of this ſad Tragedy,</l>
               <l>Which well may make a flinty heart to bleed,</l>
               <l>Enlarging much our humane miſery;</l>
               <l>Yet if we marke what after did ſucceed,</l>
               <l>This might be borne; The next might well confound</l>
               <l>The ſtouteſt heart that euer walkt on gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This noble Father left a peerleſſe Sonne,</l>
               <l>As to his honor, ſo his vertues heire,</l>
               <l>VVho from all Britiſh youths the garland wonne,</l>
               <l>In vertue, learning, piety ſo rare,</l>
               <l>That he that of his praiſe ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uld volumes write,</l>
               <l>Need neuer feare the ſtile of Paraſite.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>In huma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne learning he did ſo excell,</l>
               <l>That bred in Court, he ſhamed quite the ſchooles;</l>
               <l>No Arts, few tongues, but he did know them well.</l>
               <l>Long-ſtudied-Clarks, themſelues accounted fools;</l>
               <l>Hearing his graue diſcourſe of matters ſage,</l>
               <l>Admir'd his ripenes in ſo tender age.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Religion found from cradle he imbrac't,</l>
               <l>Profeſſing it with zeale and purity,</l>
               <l>Few of his ranke in eminency plac't,</l>
               <l>VVere ſo renownd for ſincere piety:</l>
               <l>Nor did it ſwimme and float vpon the braine,</l>
               <l>Nor role on Tongue, but fixt in heart remaine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This bloſſome faire, this hopefull tender plant,</l>
               <l>VVhich ſo much fruit did promiſe Church and State,</l>
               <l>Alas, alas, my heart doth throb and pant,</l>
               <l>My tongue's benumd, and cannot well relate;</l>
               <l>VVithin one yeere after his fathers death,</l>
               <l>Did likewiſe loſe his deareſt vitall breath.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>VVhat heart can now conceiue the wofull plight,</l>
               <l>Of that ſad Lady, that at once deſpoild</l>
               <l>Of Husband, S nne, of all that to her might</l>
               <l>Contentment yeeld; Her face with teares beſoyld,</l>
               <l>Her breſt with ſwellings, throbs and ſighs quite rent,</l>
               <l>If heau'n had not both ſtrength and comfort ſent.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:18375:71"/>
               <l>Such Lord, ſuch ſonne, few Ladies euer gaind,</l>
               <l>And therefore none haue taſted ſuch a loſſe,</l>
               <l>The happineſſe w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ich ſhe before attaind,</l>
               <l>Double<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h the griefe, and greater makes the croſſe:</l>
               <l>The loſſe was great, the croſſe much greater ſute;</l>
               <l>Thanks to the Lord who ſtrength gaue to endure.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet may we well that mother happy deeme,</l>
               <l>That brought to light ſo great an ornament</l>
               <l>Vnto this land; that we may iuſt eſteeme</l>
               <l>VVhole months, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re yeeres in teares and ſorrow ſpent</l>
               <l>For his vntimely death, his ſudden fall,</l>
               <l>VVhich hath amaz'd and terrifi'd vs all.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Who doth not ſee the dreadfull glorious God,</l>
               <l>Threaten this Realme with iudgements manifold,</l>
               <l>(VVhen thus he ſhakes at vs his iron rod,)</l>
               <l>Is too Mole-blind; this ſay I dare be bold,</l>
               <l>Pillars demoliſht of a pallace great,</l>
               <l>The ruine of the frame do truly threat.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Since that tall Cedar, chiefe of all the reſt,</l>
               <l>Prince HENRY fell by ſad diſaſtrous fate,</l>
               <l>No one that grew in our Engliſh forreſt.</l>
               <l>Gaue ſuch a blow vnto the Church and ſtate:</l>
               <l>He was too good for vs, vnworthy we</l>
               <l>Of ſuch a treaſure, ſuch felicity.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>His vertues haue him call'd aboue the ſtars,</l>
               <l>Earth was vnworthy ſuch a diamon,</l>
               <l>He novv partakes not of our brawles and iars,</l>
               <l>For mourning weeds white robes he hath put on.</l>
               <l>Sinne, griefe, and teares haue tane them to their wings,</l>
               <l>And with the Lambe he Hallelu-iah ſings.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then let vs ceaſe for to bewaile with teares,</l>
               <l>That happy ſoule, poſſeſſing heauenly ioyes</l>
               <l>That no tongue can expreſſe, no humane eares</l>
               <l>Hath euer heard, no earthly wit can poyſe:</l>
               <l>Let vs lament our ſelues our ſinfull liues,</l>
               <l>VVhich of ſo precious iewels vs depriues.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>By F.H.D.M.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:18375:72"/>
            <head>An Epitaph vpon the ſaid rightly honored Lord in life and death, in Engliſh Iambicks.</head>
            <l>HEre liet Lord Harington, the ſecond of that houſe,</l>
            <l>Who ſcarcely left his ſecond in the Brittiſh Ile,</l>
            <l>In honour true, in vertue, matchleſſe pietie.</l>
            <l>The Phaenix of our age, in whoſe graue countenance</l>
            <l>The graces ſat, the Muſes lodged in noble Breſt.</l>
            <l>At twenty yeares whoſe wiſdome great did farre excell</l>
            <l>The hoary head of long and good experience.</l>
            <l>Too good for earth; fit to adorne the higheſt heauens:</l>
            <l>Where now his ſoule liues, raignes in celeſtiall ioyes;</l>
            <l>His body here reſeru'd till the laſt iudgement day,</l>
            <l>His name like ointment ſweet through all Europa ſmells,</l>
            <l>And ſhall ſo long as vertue and religion,</l>
            <l>Shall find renowne in theſe cold Nothern Climats.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>By F H.D.M.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>Another Epitaph.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>HEere lies interred young Lord <hi>Harington,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Heire to his Fathers worth and dignitie,</l>
               <l>And now by too too ſoone ſucceſſion</l>
               <l>Of fathers fates, heire to eternity:</l>
               <l>His body in his grand dames boſome is:</l>
               <l>His minds ſuru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ving vertues ſpeake his bliſſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>His noble birth to learned Arts mode way,</l>
               <l>His learned arts on vertue ſtill attended,</l>
               <l>His vertue on true piety did ſtay,</l>
               <l>His piety hath him to God comm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nded,</l>
               <l>His birth, his Arts, vertues and pious grace,</l>
               <l>Alot him earths large praiſe, and heauens place.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Church tels what a patron now is gone,</l>
               <l>The Common-weale did him a pillar deeme,</l>
               <l>He was his houſes hope, truthes Champion.</l>
               <l>The good mans friend, indeed, as he did ſeeme.</l>
               <l>Their patro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, pillar, champion, hope and friend<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>They waile, and marke where miſery will end.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>I.P. Cant. Coll. Syd. Suff.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:18375:72"/>
            <head>To the liuing memory of the late and <hi>laſt S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>.</hi> Iohn Harington <hi>Knight, Lord Harington,</hi> Baron of Exton.</head>
            <lg>
               <head>To the Booke.</head>
               <l>GOe and ſpeake tru h; It is thy office now,</l>
               <l>Not onely to enforme our liues, but how</l>
               <l>By <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> are examples miracles agree,</l>
               <l>With praiſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, and wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h praecepts: This was hee.</l>
               <l>His praiſe will not diſhonour ſimple truth,</l>
               <l>To ſay but what he was; and but a youth.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>To the World.</head>
               <l>If thou wert all dull earth, I ſhould beleeue;</l>
               <l>Thou hadſt no ſence to feele: nor ſoule to greeue,</l>
               <l>But ô thou art compol'd of ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ler parts,</l>
               <l>And ſee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t thy loſſe engrauen in our hearts;</l>
               <l>The pureſt part, of all thou art (alas</l>
               <l>How fraile, art thou then) was as fraile as graſſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>To England.</head>
               <l>Thou haſt beene beaten many thouſand yeares:</l>
               <l>VVith ſeas; and yet art ſafe, But ô teares</l>
               <l>VVill more endaunger thee: he was in thee</l>
               <l>The Hand, thou the ſea; where ſuch men bee</l>
               <l>Bea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en with rage of changes; yet they ſtand</l>
               <l>Safe in themſelues and fix'd as any land.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>To his Mother, and ſiſters<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </head>
               <l>Rather then tell how good he was; I will</l>
               <l>Perſwade you to forget: yet weepe your fill.</l>
               <l>For ſuch a Sonne, O death, and ſuch a brother</l>
               <l>Is rare as heauens great eye; that hath no other.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>To his Friends.</head>
               <l>To all that vertue loue, I doe commend</l>
               <l>This title; It was al one to be his friend</l>
               <l>And good; who hath no claime and title now</l>
               <l>He doth not him, but vertue diſauow;</l>
               <l>And yet he had one nearer, then the reſt,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>.</hi> Ed. Harwood.</note>
               </l>
               <l>He liu'd at houſhold with him: we at feaſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:18375:73"/>
               <head>To the Arts.</head>
               <l>Ioy he is gon; he would haue diu'd into</l>
               <l>Your deepeſt ſecrets, and your knots vndo.</l>
               <l>As vnknown <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ricks, diſcouerd eaſy ſeeme,</l>
               <l>He would to v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> reduce you; not eſteeme.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>To Religion.</head>
               <l>What haſt thou loſt, ô ſacred miſterie.</l>
               <l>Thy Nurſe, and yet thy Childe? He did not die</l>
               <l>To thee, of all the reſt: he was aliue</l>
               <l>They martyr, and now dead, he doth more thriue,</l>
               <l>In thee: ô no: his ſtate takes no increaſe?</l>
               <l>Full of the ioies of God: he liues in peace.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>To Death.</head>
               <l>Poore vncreated nothing; to contend</l>
               <l>To make all things like thee; yet miſſe thy end.</l>
               <l>Canſt thou hold him one houre, ô enuious death,</l>
               <l>Or touch his laſt, yet euerlaſting breath;</l>
               <l>O No: that fled where thou ſhalt neuer come,</l>
               <l>Though here a while thou triumph on his Toombe.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:18375:73"/>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thomas Roe,</hi> Knight.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>draped coffin</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
